<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most glorious representation of the incomparable free grace of Christ, faithfully, fully, and freely offering himself, at all times, by all manner of means, to all sorts of sinners, under the sound of the gospel. Answering all objections, of all sorts of men, which formerly kept them from coming to Him. Stating the question about universall redemption, in an unusuall way, whereby to escape the rocks on both sides, on which many have split: confuting them that do denie justification by faith; and others assertion of eternall actuall justification, before men do beleeve. Setling many cases of conscience that arise in a perplexed soul about his inward spirituall condition. And lastly prescribing severall divine soliloquies, and soul-wrastlings with Christ, whereby to fall in, and fully close with him by faith. Lisenced by authoritie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89364</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865086</idno>
  <idno type="VID">117321</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240903883</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E603_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205829</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865086</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865086e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117321)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E603[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most glorious representation of the incomparable free grace of Christ, faithfully, fully, and freely offering himself, at all times, by all manner of means, to all sorts of sinners, under the sound of the gospel. Answering all objections, of all sorts of men, which formerly kept them from coming to Him. Stating the question about universall redemption, in an unusuall way, whereby to escape the rocks on both sides, on which many have split: confuting them that do denie justification by faith; and others assertion of eternall actuall justification, before men do beleeve. Setling many cases of conscience that arise in a perplexed soul about his inward spirituall condition. And lastly prescribing severall divine soliloquies, and soul-wrastlings with Christ, whereby to fall in, and fully close with him by faith. Lisenced by authoritie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M: Symmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Grace.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117321:1"/>
            <p>A MOST GLORIOUS REPRESENTATION OF THE INCOMPARABLE FREE GRACE OF CHRIST, Faithfully, fully, and freely offering himself, at all times, by all manner of means, to all sorts of Sinners, under the sound of the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>Answering all Objections, of all sorts of men, which formerly kept them from coming to Him.</p>
            <p>Stating the Question about Universall Redemption, in an unusuall way, whereby to escape the rocks on both sides, on which many have split: Confuting them that do denie Justification by Faith; and others assertion of eternall actuall Justification, before men do beleeve.</p>
            <p>Setling many <hi>Cases of Conscience</hi> that arise in a perplexed Soul about his inward spirituall condition.</p>
            <p>AND LASTLY Prescribing <hi>severall divine Soliloquies, and Soul-wrastlings with Christ,</hi> whereby to fall in, and fully close with him by faith.</p>
            <p>Lisenced by Authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M: Symmons.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117321:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117321:2"/>
            <head>CHRIST HIS Full and free Offer of himselfe To poore SINNERS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 6.37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Him that commeth to me, I will in no wise cast out.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I</hi> The footing and meaning of the maine Proposition of Christs offer of himselfe cleared.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold here a <hi>wonderfull</hi> chapter; this is part of the Zodiack, that line of heavenly Gospell, in which the <hi>Sunne of Righteousnesse</hi> moves, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Climat below in the Church, to seeing men, must needes be full of <hi>wonderfull</hi> light and glory. Here is nothing but <hi>miracula aut miranda, miracles,</hi> or <hi>marvels:</hi> the former setting off the latter; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preferred afore the former.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Here is a <hi>miraculous Epulation;</hi> a feeding five thousand with five barley loves, and two small fishes; and that unto such
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117321:3"/> satiety and alacrity, as if feasted with plenty, and dainties, <hi>verse</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See what browne bread with the Gospel is, when the <hi>Provision</hi> is but little, and little worth, but the Gospel is come, and become the sauce, there is great <hi>cheere, Acts</hi> 2.46. <hi>Continuing dayly in the Temple, and breaking bread from house to house, they eate their meate with gladnesse and singlenesse of heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A <hi>miraculous evasion,</hi> or escape of Christ, from being made King by force. Marvellous not onely in regard of his power, but of his will <hi>He was a King, he professeth himselfe to be a King, and that to that end he was borne, and for that cause he came to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the truth,</hi> and therefore to <hi>that</hi> truth, <hi>John</hi> 18.37. Yet here <hi>when he perceived that they would come, and take him by force, and make him a King, he departed into a mountaine himselfe alone.</hi> He would not be a King, that he might be a King. He disclaimed <hi>Civill</hi> pompous Royalty, that he might be proclaimed a <hi>Spiritual</hi> King. The world from their earthly principles inferre their earthly conclusions: the <hi>Heathens</hi> (as have the <hi>Jewes,</hi>) wrote those for Gods that were eminent Authours <hi>eorum quae ad victum conducunt</hi> of husbandry, victualing of Kingdomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Apis</hi> was invented on some such occasion; and perhaps (as some thinke) in after times upon <hi>Josephs</hi> saving <hi>Egypt</hi> in the time of famine. But Christ intends in that miracle of <hi>bread,</hi> in the miracles of <hi>healing diseases,</hi> to lead them to consider him as a <hi>Spirituall Physician,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 8.17. compare Isay 53.4.</note> to suggest to them that he was the true <hi>spirituall bread, ver.</hi> 48. And therefore waves the offer of a Crowne for his breaden exploit, and although with violence they would have put it on, he without violence escapes it, and them.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A <hi>miraculous perambulation;</hi> he walkes on the sea, <hi>verse</hi> 19. not so much to invite a <hi>Peter</hi> to aske power to doe so too, (and <hi>Peters</hi> designe in part miscarried, to the feare of his life,) but to cause men to looke higher, <hi>viz.</hi> that he that now walkes on the fluid flouds, is he that came downe from heaven, God in humane flesh,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note>
                  <hi>(O the great mystery)</hi> and would walke up thither againe upon the non feather-bearing ayre, as upon solid ground, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. So <hi>ver.</hi> 38. of this 6. of <hi>Iohn I came downe from heaven,</hi> ver. 39. <hi>That I should rayse them that the Father hath given me,</hi> that so they may be where he should be. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.2, 3.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117321:3"/>
               <p>But all these are but <hi>corporall miracles,</hi> they did tend immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately but to the body; but intended to in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>scate the bodily sences to guide them thence, and guide the soule towards <hi>spirituall maer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells;</hi> As</p>
               <p n="1">1 To those <hi>marvellous Expressions,</hi> what Christ is. From <hi>ver.</hi> 22. to the Text. <hi>viz.</hi> That he is not a Cooke or Kitchen-Christ for the body, but the soule-saving Christ, for a mans spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To that <hi>marvelous Protestation,</hi> who shall have him, and be the better for him spiritually, in the Text: namely, <hi>Him that commeth to him, he will in no wise cast out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Him that cometh]</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The</hi> or <hi>that</hi> coming man, who or whatsoever he be, noted by an emphaticall article, <hi>Quam pulchrum est digito monstrari dicier hic est:</hi> What a blessed thing is it to be pointed out with the finger who shall be welcome to Christ: and with such a facil, and low condition or note: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>coming;</hi> The Gospel definition of the weakest true faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e heavy laden, &amp;c. Heb.</hi> 7.25. He will save to the utmost <hi>them that come to God by him, Rev.</hi> 22.17. Let him that is <hi>a thirst come,</hi> and <hi>whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will come.</hi> So here, <hi>Him that cometh will I in no wise cast out;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">A lively proof that by comming, Christ means beleeving is Ioh. 7.37.38. v. 37. <hi>If any thrist let him come,</hi> and v. 38. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h on me out of his belly shall slow rivers.</hi>
                  </note> He saith, not him that beleeveth in expresse termes, as namely faith in all its latitude, (which is strong as well as weake,) and including all its acts which sometimes <hi>exults,</hi> as well as <hi>adhers;</hi> least thus he should have amazed a poore sinner, that but now is turning the first looke towards Christ, moving the first step to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Christ: but names the lowest act of faith, that he is some how nestling towards Christ. Christ saith not <hi>him that is running,</hi> for that imports <hi>speed</hi> and <hi>clearenesse</hi> in beleeving and moving to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Christ, which many a poore sinner hath not in a long time. He saith not <hi>Him that is skipping,</hi> which imports <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>triumph;</hi> which are hid from many a poore soule most of his life time. But him that is <hi>coming,</hi> though but <hi>tumbling</hi> in the dust of his owne unworthinesse, <hi>rowling</hi> on Gods footstoole the earth towards the throne of grace, (as faith, yea the faith of Christ is described, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.8.<note n="†" place="margin">In the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Rowle,</hi> &amp; it's sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ken of Christ in his agony or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion on the Crosse, <hi>Psa.</hi> 22.1, 2. &amp;c. yet called <hi>saith</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mat. 27.42. And therefore likely h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wling</hi> is by our <hi>Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>red <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rusting.</hi>
                  </note>) Him that is <hi>coming,</hi> though lamenting, doubting, disputing, but coming; there are some things, some actings of faith of adherence and recumbence, though yet not of assurance.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117321:4"/>
               <p>Adde this <hi>[Him that cometh]</hi> is but in the <hi>participle,</hi> viz <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and that too of the present tence or time, <hi>now coming,</hi> the <hi>first</hi> noting continuance of motion, and not to give a start for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and then goe backe, as <hi>ver.</hi> 66. after the Text. But is still coming onwards towards Christ; he is rowling towards Christ, (as Christ in his desertion towards God, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.) though not yet rested on Christ. The second noting his instantaneous and presentnesse of spirit now at the first reall discoveries of Christ that he cannot come too soone, before Christ is ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive him. Adde, that it is spoken in the <hi>singular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and of a <hi>single person.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the former part of the <hi>verse,</hi> the expression is a Nowne of multitude, and in a most collective way, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>all,</hi> as if <hi>all things,</hi> or (as <hi>Marke</hi> 16.15.) <hi>every creature,</hi> that the Father giveth me, shall come to me; but here in the Text the expression intimates <hi>a single person.</hi> So that though our poore lonely person in a place, come towards Christ, he comes not by example in in the crowd, as others in this chapter; yea though they dishear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him, yet he hearkens to Christ; he thinkes to find favour with Christ, though others will not countenance him in it: this is according to Christs minde and heart, he will bid him wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. <hi>Him, that is never so lonely, wondred at of all his neighbours, if he make towards me, he will in no wise refuse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, note further, that the expression, <hi>him that cometh,</hi> is every way <hi>indefinite;</hi> as it is not expressely universall, so it is not explicitly particular, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> but left unlimited. But you will object, that it is limited in the beginning of the <hi>verse,</hi> saying, <hi>All that the Fatber giveth me, shall come unto me.</hi> So that none can <hi>come</hi> but whom the Father giveth; Now it is a question, whether the Father hath given me to Christ, and so whether ever he will give Christ to me? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
                  </label> To which a word now, more anon, that this doth no more import any limitation in Gods <hi>mind,</hi> in regard of <hi>election,</hi> then in the <hi>Text</hi> of Gods <hi>promulgation,</hi> and offer of Christ to thee. For as this offer of Christ is expressed indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt, so also is election expressed indefinitely in the Context: <hi>All that the Father giveth,</hi> and so thou hast no more warrant to exclude thy selfe from the one, then from the other;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117321:4"/> when God doth expresse no exclusion of thee from either. Yea, thou hast reason to include thy selfe within the election, when thou commest to Christ, upon this or the like promulgation. For thou hast here a demonstration that thou art <hi>elected,</hi> because thou <hi>comest.</hi> As Christ intends to prove that these <hi>Jewes</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse Christ, are not elected because they come not. If thou come saith Christ, <hi>I shall in no wise cast thee out:</hi> therefore thou art one of the elect. It being a sure signe of one within the election, that he is taken, affected and drawne with the doctrine os electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to venter his soule upon it, as others now in heaven have done; and this perswasion drawing him <hi>saveable,</hi> to Christ to be <hi>saved;</hi> the conclusion in the Text is beyond all peradventure, <hi>That Christ will not cast such a soule off, no by no meanes;</hi> as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In no wise]</hi> The Greeke, for emphasis and vehemency of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, to import the certainty of the thing, and the affection of Christ, useth two <hi>negatives,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the best <hi>French</hi> translate <hi>Ne point,</hi>) as we say in <hi>English, No by no meanes.</hi> It is usuall with God-Christ when he speakes of some great thing to men; that it may not seeme to be too good to be true, that he use more then one <hi>negative,</hi> in Text two, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13:5. The last clause, <hi>I will not forsake thee,</hi> is in the Greeke, as in the Text, with a double <hi>negative,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>I will by no meanes forsake thee;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> yea in that fift <hi>verse</hi> and the whole of the latter part are five negatives in the Greek, as if he should say, <hi>I will not, not leave thee, yea I will not, not, not forsake thee.</hi> Christ like a true hearted woer makes many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in one full sentence, in one breath, that he will be faithfull to the soule. He will not, he will not (as it followes)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cast out]</hi> who ever comes, comes by the <hi>Fathers power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Compare. ver. 44.</note> so in the Context, therefore the Sonne will not take upon him the authority to cast him out. The Father sends him, therefore the <hi>Sonne in love to the Father,</hi> cannot find in his heart to refuse him. He that comes is <hi>a gift</hi> of the Father, bestowed on Christ, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ cannot but accept. <hi>He will not cast out,</hi> that is, he also will receive him in. As by the Fathers <hi>donation</hi> sent to Christ, so by Christs <hi>acceptation</hi> taken into himselfe and into the Church into mysticall union. And all this Christ protesteth in the <hi>future
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117321:5"/> tense,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bez. Piscat.</note>
                  <hi>or time,</hi> and that indicatively, though some read it <hi>potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> and as in the <hi>present tense, I may by no meanes cast out:</hi> And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reason of this varying is because the body of the Greeke word in the <hi>present time</hi> and the <hi>future</hi> in <hi>subjunct▪ mood</hi> is all one. [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] the difference is onely in the Accent (a late invention) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in the present time. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in the future, but more safe to take it in the future tense, (as the <hi>Syriac</hi> doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> I will not cast out, and the best <hi>French</hi> translate <hi>it ne i etteray point,</hi> I will in no case cast out.) For Christs words import, those that are coming to him from time to time in succeeding ages: and therefore must make the plaister commensurate to the soare. Besides the future tense is comprehensive, and includes all tenses,<note n="*" place="margin">That which will or shall be must needs include <hi>is</hi> or hath beene.</note> which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why the Holy Ghost so often useth in the Old-Testament, the future time, for the past or present. And as thus Christ en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth himselfe for <hi>time,</hi> so for degree: he would not cast him <hi>out and out:</hi> So the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Though Christ may cast him <hi>out</hi> of <hi>helpe</hi> sometime: yet not <hi>out and out</hi> not out of <hi>helpe</hi> and out of <hi>hope</hi> too. Though out of deliverance, yet not out of support too. Though out of sence and feeling of Christs power in him, yet not out of Christs safety and preservation of him. Christ will hold the child whiles it doth cry, till it sucke and be stilled.</p>
               <p>So that all things considered, we have cleare-footing for this summary position touching Christs offer of himselfe to sinners, <hi>That Christ doth most freely and fully hold forth himselfe to receive his, and not cast out any that come to him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The maine Proposition.</note>
                  <hi>Freely,</hi> in regard of affection, <hi>Fully,</hi> in regard of his expression, <hi>will in no wise.</hi> Our Saviour seemes to speake in opposition to the manner of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who for a trifle would cast out a man; yea for wel-doing, <hi>John</hi> 9.35. But saith Christ, <hi>I will in no wise cast out any commers to me.</hi> Or in way of intimation of a reproofe of the world, that <hi>cast out the Saints names for naught, Luke</hi> 6.22. But (saith Christ) <hi>I will in no wise cast out them that come.</hi> Or by way of aggravation of the sinne of the <hi>Jewes</hi> in neglecting Christ, that they perished voluntarily, if not obstinately, <hi>John</hi> 5.39, 40.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117321:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Christs free and full offer of himselfe to fainting sinners, by foure Votes of Scripture <hi>duely extended,</hi> each har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniously clearing the other, and all sweetly cheering the doubting soule.</head>
               <p>THis sole-soule-saving point of Christs free and full offer of himselfe to sinners is much <hi>darkened</hi> by the doctrines of men, and <hi>dedignified</hi> by the doubting soules that are invited by it; and therefore much is spoken for it in the Scripture; especially four scriptures fully vote it <hi>a law for faith:</hi> (as evermore Christ is most tender of his tender ones to repeate and inculcate comfort for them, under the notions of <hi>heavy, laden, Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Hungerers, Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bruised reedes, Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>Lambes, John</hi> 21.15.) I say four Scriptures most amply inact and set forth this Proposition of Christs offer of himselfe, as the onely <hi>law of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Script. <hi>John</hi> 3.7, 8. <hi>Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him come to me, and drinke: He that beleeveth on me, out of his belly shall flow rivers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Script. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Let him that is a thirst, come, and whosoever will let him take of the water of life freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Script. The Text, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>Him that cometh to me, I will in no wise cast out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Script. <hi>Isai.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Ho every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eate, yea come buy wine, and milke, without money and without price.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have ordered them for a poore soules best advantage. For, as all the places have the same expression <hi>come:</hi> and the first place expounds both what is <hi>coming,</hi> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. at most <hi>beleeving</hi> with the least true faith, and what a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the <hi>waters,</hi> namely <hi>Christ;</hi> So they all have some peculiar expressions to explaine, and cleare one another, and doe lye in a just method: The second to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for the first: The third for the second, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The first place proclaimes, <hi>If any man thirst, let him come to Christ,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117321:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Saith the distressed soule; I dare not, or doe not thirst, at least as I should.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Therefore the second place <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. proclaimes, <hi>whosoever will,</hi> let him come and take of the water of life freely: It addes a <hi>Quicunque vult, a whosoever will,</hi> to explaine thirst.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But saith the poore selfe-vilifying sinner; <hi>I have no will,</hi> I rather feare then hope in coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Therefore the third Scripture, the Text <hi>John</hi> 6.37. proclaimes, <hi>That every one that comes,</hi> whether <hi>voluntate plena,</hi> or <hi>semi-plena,</hi> whether with a <hi>will,</hi> or an <hi>unwilling will,</hi> (like the Merchants <hi>will</hi> to throw his goods into the tempestuous sea to save his life,) so as he <hi>comes</hi> after Christ, though feare puts in the <hi>caveat,</hi> if he may be so bold, and some doubting puts in a <hi>Quaere,</hi> whether so great a sinner may lay claime, him will Christ Jesus in no wise cast out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But saith the sinner poore in spirit, unbottomed ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly from himselfe: <hi>I cannot come:</hi> I have no power, no grace, nothing; I stand so as to looke on, but cannot come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Therefore the fourth Scripture <hi>Isai.</hi> 55.1. proclaimes, And <hi>he that hath no money:</hi> come ye and buy: come eate: come buy wine and milke, (cherishment and nourishment,) <hi>without money, and without price:</hi> without <hi>money,</hi> or <hi>monyes-worth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> But how can one be said to buy without any thing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> (As <hi>Aug.</hi> excellently,) the meaning is, <hi>Sell thy selfe,</hi> thine owne wit, reason, selfe-worth: Part with thy selfe, and that is all Christ desires. Say not thou art <hi>unworthy,</hi> (which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies thou lookest for a worthynesse in thy selfe,) <hi>Christ dyed for ungodly, for sinners, for enemies, Rom.</hi> 5. Say not thou canst not <hi>see</hi> any <hi>reason,</hi> why Christ should save thee, (which imports as if thou wouldst make faith to be grounded on humane reason, or that thou wouldest <hi>Arminian</hi>-like reason thy self into faith,) for <hi>if any man will be wise, he must become a foole, that he may be wise,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. Faith and fight are opposite, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. We must rest upon this, that <hi>Gods thoughts are above our thoughts, Isaiah</hi> 55.8, 9.</p>
               <p>Thus these four places answer for one another, and to the perplexed sinner, unto full satisfaction in the thing, if the soule
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117321:6"/> be not at present taken and satisfied; which must be Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke, upon a soules waiting on God, for which there is a sure promise, <hi>Isai.</hi> 55:10. And it is a close of an answer to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny scruples of the doubting sinner: As <hi>the raine comes downe from heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and makes it bring forth: so shall my word be;</hi> that is, my answers, for satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of thy doubts, at last shall effectually satisfy thee.</p>
               <p>I say thus these foure places cleare each other. Yea each place of these foure is wise enough to answer for it selfe.</p>
               <p>The first place, <hi>John</hi> 7.35. saith, Every one that is <hi>thirsty,</hi> let him come.</p>
               <p>If it be objected, by the poore soule, he cannot be thirsty as he would.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> This place answereth, that by <hi>thirst,</hi> it means the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est single desire of Christ, namely to be sensible of ones neede of Christ. For first it is spoken to the <hi>Jewes</hi> that came to the feast, rested in the <hi>Jewish</hi> ceremonies, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7:4. or at most in sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 5:39, 40. But not on Christ, and therefore called those that were <hi>righteous in their owne eyes, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifiers of themselves, such as neede no repentance;</hi> that is, in their owne opinion. Therefore <hi>thirst here</hi> signifies in the lowest step; a needinesse of Christ. Secondly, <hi>Thirsting,</hi> and <hi>coming</hi> are put together: so that such a desire as moves on from ones former standing still, towards Christ must needes be here included.</p>
               <p>The sinne of <hi>presumption,</hi> yea the sinne <hi>against the Holy Ghost</hi> doth not exclud a man from salvation, as sins, but as they are <hi>such</hi> sinnes, as thinke they have no neede of Christ. One would thinke indeede that <hi>despaire</hi> were sensible enough of a neede of Christ; but this sinne is such a sinne as doth unChrist Christ; Though the despairer neede somewhat to save him, yet he doth not thinke Christ to be sufficient: but counts his guilt to be greater then Christs merit and efficacy. Therefore despai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Traitor <hi>Judas</hi> perished: when as the <hi>coming</hi> crucifiers, that <hi>came toward Christ</hi> by the preaching of <hi>Peter</hi> were saved, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>The s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cond place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22:17. <hi>Whos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ver will,</hi> let him come.</p>
               <p>If it be objected by the poore soule, he hath no will.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117321:7"/>
               <p>This place answers that <hi>voluntas semiplena est voluntas,</hi> an halfe will, an incompleate will, an unwilling will, is a will, for as it nils, so it wils too, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7:15. That which I doe I allow not, but what I would that doe I not: Yea God rich in mercy is sometimes pleased to entertaine any instinct or inclination in a man, by which he comes and lookes towards Christ, though for present, being dimme, he lookes to him sinistrously. As when sometimes a man goes to a Sermon to heare the word of Christ; but can hardly give himselfe a distinct account: why? He hath a mind to goe, and yet he is about to stay, and yet at last he goes, and yet is something unwilling while he goes, (as <hi>Israel</hi> went out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but unwillingly, if we looke on all passages.) The soule perhaps goes to a Sermon at first, rather <hi>nilling some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is not Christ,</hi> (yet such as Christ must remove,) as dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of sinne, the horror of conscience, or <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then <hi>distinctly willing</hi> Christ. (As a mayde gives her consent to a wooer, to be rid of a worse, rather then for love of him as yet,) so that a man sometimes comes to an ordinance, (and so somewhat towards Christ,) rather by a common providence, or by occasions; then by a distinct, entire, morall act of his owne will. <hi>Augustine</hi> went (as he confesseth) to heare <hi>Ambrose</hi> his eloquence of words, but is catcht with the power of his matter. So that I say God rich in mercy, is sometimes pleased to entertaine a meane will, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish that inclination which can hardly be called a morall act of the will: so that according to interpretation by divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence <hi>whomsoever will,</hi> may signifie, but as much as <hi>quemlibet, whomsoever,</hi> any how coming, neerer towards Christ where he will be found <hi>Marke</hi> 16:15. <hi>Preach the Gospell to every creature;</hi> be his will, more or lesse; direct, or indirect and oblique.</p>
               <p>The third place, <hi>John</hi> 6:37. <hi>Him that comes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the poore soule object, he <hi>cannot come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This place answers that all coming must be included, though yet he cannot <hi>move with a distinct act of faith;</hi> for till Christ doth radiat on the soule, there is no act of seeing: nor can he yet <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour spiritually for Christ.</hi> For he cannot make bricks till straw be given him: But he comes to an ordinance, &amp; becomes a waiter on this ordinance: he lookes towards a Saviour in an ordinance,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117321:7"/> by that common knowledge he learnes at an ordinance. As many looked to the brazen serpent, who at first had not faith to be healed. If Christ must looke on converted <hi>Peter,</hi> before he can repent of that particular failing in denying his Master, then sure Christ must looke on unconverted <hi>Paul,</hi> before he can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</p>
               <p>The fourth place, <hi>Isai.</hi> 55.1. <hi>He that hath no money, nor price, let him come and buy:</hi> let him sell himselfe, and he shall buy Christ.</p>
               <p>If the poore soule object here, that he a poore non-convert cannot sell himselfe, part with his owne wit, reason and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming righteousnesse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This place answers, First, That he may <hi>legally,</hi> though not <hi>evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelically:</hi> As thirst imports in part a heat &amp; drought of the soule by the doctrine of the <hi>fiery law</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> as the Scriptures call it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That by attending to the doctrine of the Gospell, he shall be wrought to an <hi>evangelicall</hi> thirst after Christ. That is, this text and the like propounding Christ in his excellencies, as under the notions of milke, wine, fatnesse, and dainties, they shall make the palat or mouth of the poore soule water after Christ, for his lovelynesse sake. So that as thirst makes thee come: so he that propounds Christ to the thirsty will make thee thirst.</p>
               <p>So that we conclude with this generall answer for all the foure places joyntly drawne out of them. That as all these places are Christs word: so they import that this Doctor or Teacher of the Churches must be he that workes in his Disciples or Scholars to <hi>thirst,</hi> to <hi>will,</hi> to <hi>come,</hi> to <hi>sell</hi> ones selfe. For grace is wrought by the word. <hi>Faith comes by hearing.</hi> The word is the word of life. While <hi>Peter spake these words, the Holy Ghost fell on them all which heard, Acts</hi> 10.44. So that Christ that makes these conditions, makes thee so conditioned, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>For it is God that worketh in you to will and to doe of his good pleasure.</hi> Whiles he preacheth the condition, he makes the impression: when by common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring grace, Christ makes thee coming off of thy selfe, he is coming towards thee; Christ approaching, thou art made to be effectually coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117321:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the proportion and equall latitude of <hi>Election,</hi> and <hi>Redemption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr further clearing of what hath beene said, thi Question would be solved, whether <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Redemption</hi> are not some-how opposite? for election is exprest but of some, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is offered to all. To which we answer, though we toucht it afore. That though redemption it selfe, be in the first act larger then election: <hi>viz.</hi> in Christ drying in the common nature of man, not in that of Angels, &amp; thereby brings humane nature nearer to salvation, then the common nature of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; so that mans nature in generall, is <hi>saveable,</hi> whereas wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Angels are not (<hi>For verely he tooke not on him the nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, hut he tooke on him the Seede of Abraham, Heb.</hi> 2.16. which is but the renewing of that covenant with <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3.15.) For otherwise men under the Gospell, could not be justly dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for unbeliefe, but would be threatned for not beleeving a ly, namely that Christ died for them, when as in no sort he did. But this distinction of Christs dying for the common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, solves that difficulty, shewes what interest all men have in Christs redemption, and the fault of them to whom it is made knowne, in not claiming it and closing with it: I say though in this first act, <hi>redemption</hi> seemes of a greater latitude then ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet in the last and ultimate act they are equall; which last act is to make <hi>particular persons,</hi> (that are onely <hi>saveable</hi> in in the <hi>common nature,</hi>) to be actually <hi>saved</hi> in their particular persons: which is done by Christ <hi>speciall act</hi> of mediatourship, viz. <hi>intercession,</hi> John 17.20. <hi>I pray for them which shall beleeve on me:</hi> whereas the other of <hi>saveablenesse</hi> is done by Christs <hi>common act</hi> of mediatorship of making attonement by death.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10.</note> So that evenly to an haire those onely that are elected, are actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed. For though in Gods election there be no <hi>necessity of compulsion:</hi> yet there is in it a <hi>necessity of infallibility;</hi> of infalibility else God should not know what would befall his owne purposes.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117321:8"/> Yet not of <hi>compulsion;</hi> and therefore we must not charge that upon election which belongs not to it. As that non-election doth effect and force us out of salvation. We must not confound Gods decree, and the execution of his decree, or cut off the rest of the links of Gods predestination, namely vocation, justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conformation to Christ, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 8. from the first act of Election choosing of some, and so on the contrary. For non-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection cannot dammne us, unlesse we refuse vocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as thus, election and redemption in themselves, in the <hi>thing,</hi> are of equall latitude, so also in the <hi>promulgation</hi> or off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r in the Doctrine of the Gospell. The Gospell holding out <hi>electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> indefinitly to us, (though determinated with God,) <hi>The Lord knoweth them that are his,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. And that <hi>THEM,</hi> to be a great many, though defines not to us how many: of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ws,</hi> 144000. (a certaine number for an uncertaine,) but of all <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, a great multitude which no man could number,</hi> Revel. 7.4.9. And <hi>redemption</hi> indefinitely that <hi>Christ died for ungodly, for sinners, for enemies.</hi> For men voide of grace, ordinary sinners, and extraordinary, that had opposed him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>So that as redemption under an indefinite notion is offered to all, so election is held forth under the same notion to all, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially to all to whom the doctrine of these doth come: So that as faith must looke to the indefinite promise of redemption, so love must looke to the indefinite expression of Gods electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Men must throw themselves downe under the indefinite expression of election, lye under the beames of the doctrine thereof, to see if it beget a <hi>loving opinion</hi> in them, that God is willing to save sinners, (and so them) having purposed it from all eternity: and throw themselves under the powerfull sound of the promises of redemption, to waite till they worke a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving perswasion, that God hath actually redeemed them: therefore thoughts of election, if right thoughts, doe not beate a soule off from redemption, but makes way, and puts him on, being the foundation of all. And who ever hath the first, hath the last, or hath the last, hath the first. And though neither of them are absolutely <hi>of all;</hi> yet their indefinite doctrine and tender should in our eye that live under the Gospell, seeme
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117321:9"/> more wishly to looke towards, and intend us (unlesse we refuse) and to conceive more rationally, that the non-elect, and non-redeemed are those to whom the Gospell never came, or was never by them entertained. For God hath not expressely exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor doth he utterly cast thee off, till thou cast him off, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.15, 16. <hi>They mocked the messengers of God, and despised his word, till the wrath of the Lord came upon them, and there was no remedy,</hi> Prov. 29.1. <hi>He that being often reproved hardened his necke, shall come to destruction without remedy.</hi> And in the New-Testament onely for the sinne of <hi>refusing Christ</hi> all along is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation pronounced, unpardonablenesse pronounced. Thou oh man demurrest about Gods decree, and reprobation, but who gave thee leave to meddle with the secret things of God: heare his <hi>revealed things which he saith belongs to thee;</hi> God doth not actually cast thee off beyond all remedy, till thou actually cast off him; and so casts thee off, not for originall sinne, but actuall sinne, and that to not for every actuall sinne, but for those that cast off the <hi>remedy,</hi> namely the word of Christ, and Christ the word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The bottome dived into: Christs heart looked into, for security to a poore soule, that Christ can find in his heart thus freely and fully to offer himselfe to him.</head>
               <p>THus we have presented you with high expressions of Christs good will to sinners: but because man as man, is hardly drawne to be confident on bare dictates of words; we dare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the point to the dint of divine reason.</p>
               <p>First, Christ is <hi>God,</hi> therefore most <hi>naturally</hi> good: good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is his essence, mercy, compassion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His essence, Christ is God, therefore <hi>infinitely</hi> good: he cannot be God, and be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited of goodnesse: because good therefore communicative of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117321:9"/> himselfe: first, because <hi>naturally</hi> good, therefore his offer of himselfe to doe good to a sinner is <hi>free, Psal.</hi> 119. <hi>Thou art good, and dost good.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Being justified freely by his grace.</hi> Things and persons of the noblest natures are most freely boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull of themselves. The Sunne to communicate light, and life to the world, men of great birth and breeding of a free,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.23.</note> franke spirit, like <hi>Araunah:</hi> therefore the Hebrew word<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ad dandum moveri <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> voluntarius, liberalis, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificus, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps.</note> that signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a noble man, signifies <hi>free,</hi> or <hi>voluntary,</hi> or <hi>bountifull.</hi> God is essentially that of which there is but an impresse upon the creature. And because Christ as God is good enough of himselfe, he for his part needs no causes from the creature, to pump up &amp; draw out his goodnesse: Christ <hi>will be sought unto</hi> that men may owne his goodnesse, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. <hi>John</hi> 14.13, 14. But it was of Christs goodnesse to promp us with this rule: and when he suckles us, he gives the milke of the breasts of consolation freely himselfe, <hi>Isai.</hi> 66.11, 12. Secondly, because Christ as God is <hi>infinitely</hi> good, therefore the offer of himselfe is <hi>full.</hi> The sea being full of water, streames in fountaines, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 1. and flowes in rivers, offering it selfe to the adjacent Countries.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Christ is <hi>Jesus,</hi> a Saviour: so called and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, that he might <hi>save his people from their sinnes, Matth.</hi> 1.21. As he will answer to his name, will not betray his trust, be faithfull to him that put him in trust with the office of media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torship, he must save them his Father gives him to save: So it immediately followes the Tex, as arguing the assertion of the Text. <hi>Those that come to me, I will in no wise cast out, for I came downe from heaven, not to doe mine owne will, but the will of him that sent me: and this is the will of him that sent me, that every one that seeth the Sonne, and beleeveth on him, may have everlasting life.</hi> So that if it were possible, that Christ did not love us, but loved the Father onely to be obedient unto him that loveth us; this would be sufficient to offer himselfe to comfort us. So Christ argue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>John</hi> 16.26, 27. <hi>I say not I will pray the Father, for the Father himselfe loveth you.</hi> So that if Christ love the Father, and the Father us: he will for the Fathers sake doe any thing for us.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Christ as <hi>God and man</hi> must needes aime at his owne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117321:10"/> and his Fathers glory. The salvation of man is great. A soule is more worth then a world: therefore great is Gods glory in saving a soule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. two last. Now as God is infinite in lovelynesse, so Christ as God must needs infinitely love himselfe, and as man love his father: and therefore must needs be full, yea infinite in desire to advance the glory of the God-head: and so must needs be free &amp; full in his offer to promote that advancing Gods honor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Untill men come to Christ by faith, they are out of Christ, unreconciled to God, and not justified, contrary to the doctrine of eternall justification, as it is held forth by some.</head>
               <p>FRom the main position before laied downe, we are <hi>instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> and informed, that till men according to the sence of the Text, come to Christ, and are received into Christ by the spirit of faith, they are <hi>without Christ,</hi> yea <hi>without God,</hi> yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes <hi>without, John</hi> 5.39, 40. <hi>Ye search the Scriptures,</hi> (for so it should be read <hi>indicatively,</hi> not <hi>imperatively:) For in them ye thinke to have eternall life, and</hi> (indeed saith Christ,) <hi>they are they that testifie of me, and</hi> (or but) <hi>ye will not come unto me,</hi> (that is by faith,) <hi>that ye might have life;</hi> so <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.12. <hi>That in times past ye were</hi> without Christ, <hi>being aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Israel, and strangers from the covenant of promise, having no hope, and</hi> without God <hi>in the world.</hi> And therefore God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be actually reconciled to them that are not in Christ by faith. For <hi>within</hi> and <hi>without</hi> cannot be all one. But (saith the Text) men are <hi>without</hi> till they come to Christ by faith: when they come by faith, so <hi>in</hi> that they shall not be cast out. So that place of <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.12. Having teld them, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Ye are saved by grace</hi> through faith, he addes in the 12 <hi>verse,</hi> that formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ came, they were <hi>without Christ,</hi> and so <hi>without God,</hi> and shewes how, viz. <hi>being strangers from the covenant of promise,</hi> the Ground of faith. If God hath <hi>decreed,</hi> that <hi>Christ dwels in us by faith, Ephes.</hi> 3. That we are <hi>justified by faith, Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117321:10"/> Then that decree of God must be executed ere we can be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and therefore we are not to rest and relye on Gods bare decree. For as God doth not decree contradictions, namely, for a man to be <hi>within</hi> and <hi>without</hi> in the same instant, in the same respect: Reconciliation or justification being that same WITHIN; and not to be in Christ by faith is to be WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT. So twise together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Whom he foreknew he predestinated to be made conformable to his Son; whom he predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, them he called: whom he called, them also he JƲSTIFIED.</hi> So that if God himself doth not rest satisfied in a meer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose without performance, then may not we rest in Gods meer purpose of reconciliation, without his act in &amp; through Christ. As God is <hi>actually offended</hi> with sin, so there must be <hi>actuall reconciliation,</hi> in the <hi>actuall death</hi> of Christ, actually ours, by <hi>actuall faith.</hi> Else why is it said, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. last, <hi>He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the Son, shall not see life: but the wrath of God abides on him.</hi> Tis true that Gods <hi>purpose</hi> is an <hi>act</hi> of Gods minde in himself, but not an <hi>action</hi> upon his creature without him: no more then <hi>purpose of creation</hi> is creation. Or else you must say the world was actually eternall, and not created <hi>in the beginning.</hi> So that as <hi>actuall creation</hi> is not eternall; so nor <hi>actuall reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> or justification: there being no more of this eternall, then the act of Gods purpose, in time to justifie. Yet this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues no alteration in God, being onely the progression and proceeding of his unchangeable purpose, to effect according to that purpose. Which purpose is not (in Gods ordinarie way) performed without many actions to be done in time. 1. <hi>Creating</hi> or generating man, by his speciall concurrence, especially in regard of the soul. <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.18. 2. Preserving man till he grow up to a perfect understanding. 3. Teaching him by his word. So that to rest for justification in Gods meer purpose, were to make void most of Gods actions, and ordinances. But to perceive Gods actuall entring into atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with us in the application of Christ, is to see our selves exceedingly more engaged to God in love, praise and dutie; as well for his actions upon us, and in us, as for his purpose towards us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117321:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A man is justified by faith. Contrary to <hi>Samuel Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> his opinion, denying faith to have any thing to do in our justification; In his book, entitled, JƲSTIFICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION BY CHRIST ALONE. Printed by <hi>M. S. 1647.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT follows also from that text, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.3. and the main Posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thence inferred, that faith hath an hand in receiving Christ, and being received into Christ; and consequently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the many expresse votes of the Scriptures, hath an hand in our justification. As, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>And be found in him,</hi> (that is, in Christ) <hi>not having mine own righteousnesse, which is of the Law, but that which is through faith,</hi> (THE, is not in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall) <hi>of Christ, the righteousnesse which is of God by faith.</hi> Twise, you see, it is expressed, that we have righteousnesse by <hi>means of faith</hi> in two severall expressions, <hi>viz: By</hi> faith, and <hi>through</hi> FAITH of Christ, or concerning Christ, that procured that righteousnesse, we apply by faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, a man is justified by faith, without the works of the Law.</hi> Now the works of the Law are not opposite to Christ as in him. For Christ fulfilled the works of the Law for us (as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures frequently tell us) but in us, the works of the Law are opposite to faith in point of justification. And therefore it is said, we are justified by faith, beleeving that Christ satisfied the Law for us, that we might be justified <hi>gratis,</hi> as it is in that 3d. to <hi>Rom. v.</hi> 24. <hi>Being justified freely by his grace, through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Christ Jesus.</hi> Christ payed a price of <hi>redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for it. But we have it freely. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the Law, but by faith of Jesus Christ,</hi> (no article in the Greek to intimate any THE). <hi>Faith of Christ</hi> or, (which is all one) beleif of Christ (crediting his promises, and resting in his satisfaction) signifies beleeving into Jesus Christ, as it follows in this verse. <hi>Even as we have beleeved in Jesus Christ,</hi> (Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. INTO) that we might be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117321:11"/> justified, BY FAITH <hi>of Christ,</hi> (so the Greek) that is, by faith, concerning, in, upon into Christ, as is aforesaid. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8, 9, 11, 13, 14. read the place, and ponder it. As also, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. throughout the whole Chapter, giving instances in <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David;</hi> that justification is by faith. Upon which the Apostle infers in the next Chap. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being justified by faith, we have peace with God.</hi> So that vain is the shift of the Adversaries to this Doctrine to say, that the point in that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. should be removed thus: <hi>Being justified, by faith we have peace.</hi> For the other pointing thus, Being justified by faith, we have peace, doth directly answer to the Apostles dispute in the former Chapter. Besides what peace doth faith bring, but the peace of justification. It first layes hold on justification, or it can speak no peace. Lastly, that pointing, <hi>Being justified by faith,</hi> to be the right, is put out of all doubt in those places before quoted in <hi>Rom. Galat.</hi> &amp;c. where the Apostle having largely disputed the point of justification, makes it his great conclusion, that a man is justified by faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Say the Adversaries: The whole work of our salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was accomplished upon the Crosse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Not his resurrection. Yet he arose for our justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Not his intercession, yet by that we are saved: <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. And to the point in hand. Though on the Crosse he paid the price of our redemption; yet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. he prayed that we might beleeve. Subordinate things are not contrary, but sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servient. It is true, the Carpenter built the house, but it is as true, that he built it with his ax, saw, hammer, and other tools. It is certain that <hi>James</hi> payed such moneys to <hi>John;</hi> but then it is as certain, <hi>John</hi> received that money. Sure we are, Christ dyed for our justification; but it is as sure, that we are justified by faith in the death of Christ. Christ payed the price of our debt to God the Father on the Crosse. But the assignment of it to us as payed for us is by faith; as is the meaning of the Scriptures, saying, we are justified by faith.</p>
               <p>We say not we are justified by faith as it is a qualitie. So it is sanctification. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. And we are not justified by holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Nor by it as a meer act, a working qualitie; so we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117321:12"/> should be justified by a work. By somewhat we do. Nor by faith, as meerly appointed and instituted of God for that end, as to be an instrument in our justification. For then God should justifie us without reall amends to his justice. He should pay himself really offended, with an opinion that faith of it self should repay him. But we say, that we are justified by faith as an hand taking Christ. It is not the hand of it self justifies, but Christ in the hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not then sanctification in order of nature go before justification; Faith being a grace of sanctification?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Our notion of it, with submission to more light, when it shall be discovered is this. That Christ having payed for our justification in suffering for us, he comes with his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and represents the same in an immediate thought put upon our spirits by his Spirit, that this satisfaction of Christ is ours, and after that in order of nature created that thought into a standing permanent habit of faith.</p>
               <p>But to return to the opposers of justification by faith. They object, Its said by Christ on the Crosse▪ <hi>It is finished.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> The paying is finished, not the praying. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. That he doth yet continually; part of which intercession is that we may beleeve. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Where ever it is said, we are justified by faith, by faith is understood Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> This is not so. Witnesse <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. where there is mention of Christ and faith too, as both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in our justification.</p>
               <p>To conclude. Sure the opposers of justification do think, at least in part, that we are justified by faith; because they are ever and anon upon severall occasions readie to say so in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Witnesse these expressions in the book called <hi>[Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ist alone,</hi> by <hi>S. R.]</hi> namely, p. 8. Jesus Christ by once offering the sacrifice of himself on the Crosse put an end to sin. <hi>O what a fountain of consolation is here to all THAT BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEIVE. Who now may say, once sin was mine, then it was layed on Christ, and NOW they are neither mine nor his; and NOW Christs righteousnesse is mine.</hi> P. 9. <hi>Faith is given us, that by it we may live
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117321:12"/> out of our selves in another, even the Lord Jesus,</hi> &amp;c. P. 10. <hi>Christs RESƲRRECTION doth declare us to be just who BELEEVE in him.</hi> P. 15. The elect are visibly in their sins till they BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEEVE. See more of this, of the interest of faith in Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the <hi>Antidote to Antinomianisme.</hi> To which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor never replyed that I know. But Mr. <hi>Richardson</hi> did ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it a little at the end of his said Book <hi>[Justification by Christ alone.]</hi> But so slenderly, in the judgement of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Readers, as hath been confessed to me by them, that I omit to make any Duply or Answer to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Vntill men come to Christ by faith, they have not actually any saving benefit by Christs death. Where is stated and discussed the Question about Ʋniversall Redemption, of the true intent and extent thereof.</head>
               <p>TO further clear our in-being in Christ, this Question must be handled. Two extreames of opinions there are about the <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>intent</hi> of Christs death and satisfaction, that widen the difference. Which we shall now speak to (as God shall assist) for the clearing of the point in hand; and I shall not be wholly singular, but keep company with some late learned. The one extreame of opinion extendeth and violently stretcheth the death and satisfaction of Christ so much too far, as that it thinks that thereby God for his part is actually reconciled to all men, and doth really discharge every man living from all his sins, and that before faith comes. Onely they confesse, that they for their parts perceive not that benefit by it, whiles they have no faith to beleeve that God doth so love them. Now from this extreame opinion it would follow, that God should be actually reconciled to man before he did put on Christ; And that God should for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give a mans sins (which is justification) before he beleeved. Whereas the very <hi>elect</hi> themselves before their effectuall call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117321:13"/> are said to be <hi>a people not beloved. Rom.</hi> 9.25. And whiles they are <hi>without Christ to be without hope;</hi> as we heard afore out of <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>The other extreame opinion contracteth the riches of Christs satisfaction into too narrow a compasse, as if none had any interst any way therein, but such as were elected from the foundation of the world, though by the Gospel every one be charged to receive the same. Now from this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame it would follow, that a man under the Gospel should be bound in conscience to beleeve that which is untrue, and charged to take and receive that with which he hath nothing to do, namely, to beleeve, and take Christ as dying for him, when as Christ did not dye for him; nor did he belong to Christ in that respect.</p>
               <p>Some, to take away this difficultie, answer thus. That it follows onely from this argument, that some under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel are bound to beleeve an impossible thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> This solves not the knot. For, 1. I ask, will God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a soul for not beleeving that which is impossible to be had? 2. Why, say I, is it impossible for them to have Christ, but because as these men say, Christ never intended, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his death so far?</p>
               <p>Others answer to this difficultie thus. That though under the Gospel that shall never have Christ, are not bound by the voice of the Gospel to beleeve that Christ dyed for them; nor are they condemned for not beleeving that Christ dyed for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> The contrary seems to be evident, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God so loved the WORLD, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beleeveth IN HIM should not perish. Greek, INTO HIM.</hi> and v. 18. <hi>He that beleeveth on him, Gr. INTO HIM, is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: but he that beleeveth not is condemned already, because be hath not beleeved IN (Gr. INTO) the name of the onely begotten Son of God.</hi> See how God, 1. propounds his Son more general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as sent to the WORLD, and as it is in <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>He sent not his Son into the WORLD to condemne the world, but that the WORLD might be saved.</hi> Then, 2. requires men particularly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117321:13"/> to beleeve IN or INTO his Son: as <hi>HE that beleeveth in him,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore to avoid both these rocks, the word of truth, by which faith is begotten, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.13. must be sought into, to finde a middle way, wherein to go safely, and not to split against either of the said two rocks of ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urdities.</p>
               <p>For the better and readier finding out this middle and safer way, we must be carefull in the businesse of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cleerly to distinguish between the <hi>satisfaction</hi> of Christ, <hi>absolutely</hi> considered, and the <hi>application</hi> of the same <hi>relatively</hi> to men in particular. The differences are; 1. That <hi>satisfaction</hi> absolutely considered, was once, and at once done for <hi>All;</hi> but the <hi>application</hi> of it to man, is still in doing. 2. <hi>Satisfaction</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely considered, bringeth with it <hi>sufficiencie</hi> to discharge all mens whole debt; The <hi>application</hi> of it addes unto it <hi>effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie</hi> to make it effectuall. 3. The <hi>satisfaction</hi> of Christ makes the sins of mankinde onely <hi>pardonable,</hi> fit for pardon, else Gods justice could not put up the wrong done to him by sin. The particular <hi>application</hi> maketh the sins of those to whom it is applyed to be <hi>pardoned,</hi> actually and solemnly to be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by pardon. So that in summe thus. Though all sins of all men are <hi>mortall</hi> in regard of the stipend due to them by the Law; yet all do not actually bring forth eternall death; because the gracious promise of the Gospel holding forth Christ inhibits, supercedes, and stayes the execution. So that all the sins of mankinde are become <hi>veniall</hi> in respect of the price payed by Christ unto his Father; so that in shewing mercie to all, if such were his pleasure, his justice should be no looser. But all do not obtain actuall remission of sin, because most offenders do not take out, nor plead their pardon, as they ought to do. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. <hi>For all this will I be sought unto.</hi> And <hi>Isa.</hi> 55. <hi>Call upon the Lord while he is neer:</hi> and then it follows, <hi>He will abundantly pardon.</hi> If Christ had not assumed our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therein made satisfaction for the injurie offered by us to God, God would not have come to a treatie of peace with us, (as it is said, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. <hi>Come now let us reason together,</hi>) no more then with the fallen Angels, whose nature his Son Christ did not assume: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. and so were finally rejected.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117321:14"/> But this <hi>way being made through the flesh of Christ</hi> (as the Apostle speaks, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.20.) God holdeth out unto men the golden Scepter of his Gospel; and thereby not onely signifieth his pleasure of admitting them into his presence; and accepting their submission (which is a wonderfull grace, and favour) but also sendeth an embassage unto them, intreating them that they would be reconciled unto him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p>Hence is inferred against the first extremitie of opinion (of which see before) that by vertue of Christs satisfaction in our nature, God is made <hi>appeasable</hi> unto our <hi>nature;</hi> but is not actually <hi>appeased</hi> towards any mans <hi>person,</hi> untill he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Son, and put on him the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p>Hence also is inferred against the 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>: extremitie of opinion (of which afore) that all may be said to have a common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the merits of Christ: howsoever all do not injoy the benefit thereof, because they do not take it. The well spring of life is set open to all, freely. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>soever will, let him take of the water of life freely.</hi> But many fetch not, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to draw with, and the Well is deep. Faith is the onely vessell whereby we are to draw all vertue from Christ; and that is to be fetched from <hi>the hearing of the word of truth, the Gospel of our salvation. Ephes.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. which holdeth forth this bottome for every one to build his faith upon, thus.</p>
               <p>What Christ hath provided for me, and the Gospel offers to me, that I ought with all thankfulnesse to accept, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to my comfort.</p>
               <p>But Christ by his death, and obedience, hath provided a sufficient remedie for the taking away of sin, and the Gospel offereth it.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ought to accept it, and apply it to the comfort of mine own soul.</p>
               <p>Now many hearing this Gospel of salvation, do either not regard it, or not beleeve it; or if in a sort beleeve it, that is the truth of it, yet imbrace it not; but are so wedded to their sins, that they have no desire to be divorced from them: and therefore neglect the taking to themselves, and applying to their own souls this gracious offer made unto them.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117321:14"/>
               <p>Notwithstanding which neglect on their parts, we may truly say, [That good things were provided for them on Christs part,] and that <hi>a rich price was put into the hand of a fool, howsoever he had no heart to use it:</hi> Prov. 17.16. Our Saviour by that which he performed on his part hath procured a jubilee for all the sons of <hi>Adam: Luk.</hi> 4.18, 19. And the Gospel is the trumpet whereby he doth proclaim <hi>libertie to the captives, and preacheth the acceptable yeer of the Lord.</hi> If (as <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.24. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.16.) for all this some are so well pleased with their captivitie, that they desire no deliverance; this dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateth nothing from the generalitie of the <hi>freedome</hi> annexed unto that YEER. If one say to his sin, or love of the world, his old master, I love thee, I will not depart from thee, I will not go out free, then he shall be (as the servants so saying in the aforesaid texts) bored in the ear for a slave; and serve for ever. But that slavish disposition of his, maketh the extent of the priviledge of <hi>that yeer</hi> not a whit the straighter; because he was included within the generall grant as well as others, howsoever he was not disposed to take the benefit of it. The King of heaven (saith our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.2.) <hi>is like unto a certain King that made a marriage,</hi> that is, <hi>a mariage feast,</hi> as the Syriack <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> signifies) <hi>for his Son, and sent forth his servants to those that were bidden to that marriage-feast with this message, [Behold I have prepared my dinner, my oxen, and fatlings are killed, and all things are readie, come to the wedding:</hi> v. 4.] But if we look to the event, <hi>They which were bidden made light of the invitation, and went their wayes, one to his farm, another to his merchandise:</hi> v. 5. yet this neglect of theirs doth nothing falsifie the word of the King which we have in the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. verse, namely, <hi>That the dinner was prepared, and those unworthy guests were hidden thereunto.</hi> For (saith the Apostle, <hi>Rom</hi> 3.4.) <hi>What if some did not beleeve? shall their unbelief disanull the faith and truth of God? God forbid. Yea let God be true, and every man a lyar: as it is written, That thou mayest be justified in thy sayings, and overcome when thou judgest.</hi> Just as the Lord speaketh by the Prophet, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.29, 30.) <hi>Let not the house of Israel say, the way of the Lord is not equall.</hi> For when he cometh to judge them <hi>every one according to his wayes, Ezek.</hi> 33.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117321:15"/> 20. the inequalitie of the way will be found on their sides, and not on his. <hi>Oh house of Israel, are not my wayes equall; or are not your wayes unequall, saith the Lord.</hi> So in that <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his works. Psal.</hi> 145.17. <hi>All the wayes of the Lord are mercy and truth.</hi> Psal. 25.10. When we were in our sins, it was of his infinite mercie, that any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie should be provided, for our recovery. And when the medicine is prepared, we are never the nigher to actuall sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, unlesse he be pleased out of his free mercie to apply the same unto us; that so the whole praise of our redemption from the beginning to the end, may be intirely attributed to the riches of his mercie, and nothing may be left to sinfull flesh wherein to glory. The freeing of the people of the <hi>Jews</hi> from the captivitie of <hi>Babylon, (Isa.</hi> 45.1, &amp;c.) was a type of Christs great deliverance of us wrought by him. <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia</hi> (who was <hi>Christus Domini,</hi> the Christ, or the anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and herein but a type or shadow of him that is <hi>Christus Dominus,</hi> Christ the Lord, the author of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) publisheth his generall proclamation in this manner, [<hi>Who is there among you of all the people? The Lord his God be with him, and let him go up.</hi> 1 Chron. 26.33.] Now it is true that they alone did follow this calling, <hi>whose spirit God had moved to go up. Ezra</hi> 1.5. But could they therefore, that remained still be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in <hi>Babylon</hi> (1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.23.) justly plead that the Kings Grant was not large enough? or that they were excluded from going up, by any clause contained therein? Just so the matter of our redemption purchased by our Saviour Christ, lyeth open to all, all are invited to it, none that hath minde to accept it, is excluded from it. The beautifull feet of them that bring glad tydings of the Gospel of peace, do bring good news of great joy into every house wherein they tread. (<hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79 <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.) The first part of their mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage being this, <hi>Peace be to this house.</hi> But unlesse God be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed out of the abundance of his mercie to guide our feet into the way of peace, the rebellion of our nature is such, and so great, we run headlong into the <hi>wayes of destruction and misery, and the wayes of peace we do not know.</hi> (Rom. 3.16, 17. <hi>They have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117321:15"/> not all obeyed the Gospel,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16. All are not apt to entertain the message of peace. And therefore though Gods Embassadors make a true tender thereof to all to whom they are sent, yet the peace rested only <hi>upon the sons of peace.</hi> But if they meet with such as will not listen to this motion, their peace doth return again unto themselves. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.6. The proclamation of the Gospel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. runs thus: <hi>Let him that is athirst, come.</hi> For him this peace especially is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, because none but he will take the pains to come. But lest we should think this did any way abridge the largenes of that offer, a <hi>Quieun{que} vult</hi> is added in these words: <hi>And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever will, let him come and take of the waters of life freely.</hi> Yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, we must hold this, <hi>That it is God that worketh in us to will and to do of his good pleasure. Phil.</hi> 2.13. And though the call be never so loud, and so large, <hi>yet no man can come effectually, except God the Father draw him:</hi> as it is <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. For the universalitie of the satisfaction, nothing derogateth from the necessity of Gods speciall grace in the application of it. Neither doth this spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialtie of grace in the application any whit abrogate the generalitie of the satisfaction.</p>
               <p>And therefore when men urge that argument out of <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Christ PRAY'D not for the world,</hi> therefore he <hi>PAY'D</hi> not for the world; there are many considerable things may be replyed unto.</p>
               <p>For the consequence may be excepted against upon many good reasons. For though Christ did not <hi>pray</hi> for the world, yet he might <hi>pay</hi> for the world. Because this <hi>paying</hi> is a more generall or common act, of <hi>satisfaction;</hi> his praying a more speciall and choice act of <hi>intercession:</hi> so that though both acts agree in this, that they be acts of Christs Priesthood, yet in other respects are widely distinguishable. 1. <hi>Paying,</hi> that is, <hi>giving satisfaction,</hi> doth properly give content to Gods justice (as hath been shewed); <hi>Praying,</hi> that is, intercession, doth so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite Gods mercy. 2. This <hi>paying satisfaction</hi> containeth a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the plaister or potion necessarie for mans salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But <hi>praying</hi> by way of <hi>intercession,</hi> is the means of appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that remedie to the malady. 3. The <hi>paying satisfaction</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117321:16"/> belongs to the common nature of mankinde which Christ assumeth: when as <hi>praying intercession</hi> is a speciall priviledge vouchsafed to such particular persons onely as the Father hath given to his Son Christ.</p>
               <p>And therefore I think we may safely conclude from all these premisses, That the Lamb of God offering up himself (cloathed with humane nature) a sacrifice for the sins of the whole world, intended by giving satisfaction sufficiently to Gods justice, <hi>to make the nature of man</hi> (which he assumed) <hi>save<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> a fit subject for mercy, and to prepare a soveraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for the sins of the whole world, which should be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to none that minde to take the benefit thereof; howsoever he intended not, by <hi>applying</hi> this all sufficient sacrifice, or sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to every one in particular, to make it effectuall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the salvation of all, or to procure thereby, at the hands of the Father, <hi>actuall pardon</hi> for the sins of the whole world. He <hi>applyes</hi> this onely <hi>effectually</hi> to them who making claim to the satisfaction, by promise suing for the spirit and faith upon other promises, in prayer waiting for a gracious return untill they have it. So that in one respect Christ may be said <hi>to dye for all:</hi> and in another respect, <hi>not to dye for all.</hi> Yet so as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of his merit, he may be accounted a kinde of universall cause of the <hi>restoring</hi> of our nature, as <hi>Adam</hi> was of the <hi>depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of it. So that, to conclude, as far as I can discern one did curiously hit the nayl on the head,<note place="margin">Mors Christi est quasi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam universalis causa salutis, sicut peccatum primi hominis fuit quasi uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versalis causa damnationis. Oportet autem universalem causam applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ad unumquem{que} specialiter, ut effectum universalis causae ille percipiat Effectus peccati primi hominis pervenit ad unumquem{que} per carnis originem; effectus autem mortis Christi pertingit ad unumquem{que} per spiritualem regenerationem, per quam homo Christo quodamodo conjungitur, &amp; incorporatur.</note> when he determined this matter on this wise. <hi>The death of Christ is as it were a certain uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall cause of salvation; as the sin of the first man was as it were an universall cause of damnation. But an universall cause must be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to every one in speciall, that he may partake of the effect of the universall cause. The effect of the sin of the first man came upon every man by the originall of corrupt flesh; and the effect of Christs death reacheth to every one</hi> (whom it reacheth) <hi>by spirituall regeneration, by which, man is after a sort conjoyned and incorporated to Christ.</hi> So he. We will onely adde this. That as the sin of <hi>Adam</hi> was an
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117321:16"/> universal cause of eternall death unto mankinde in generall; but not to every particular man, unlesse originall corruption were derived to him, as Christs humane nature in the very conception was exempted. So the satisfaction of Christs death is for all mankinde, but is not effectuall to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man, but to him to whom Christs grace is derived.</p>
               <p>Upon all it follows. That though the fallen Angels have no encouragement at all to hearken to the Gospel, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing at all for them: yet all men to whom the Gospel shall come, have much encouragement to hearken to it in this, <hi>That Christ took upon him the common nature of mankinde, made it saveable, brought it neerer to salvation then the nature of lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Angels.</hi> And more particularly that it is said indefinitely, <hi>Christ dyed for sinners, for ungodly, for enemies.</hi> And yet more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the text, that <hi>him that cometh to him he wil in no wise cast out.</hi> I say they have encouragment to attend to the Gospel there to finde an effectuall testimony of Christs dying for them, by drawing them to beleeve it; and not to stand off, or fall on, upon notions of their own (of Christ dying FOR ALL, or if not for ALL, then NOT FOR ME) before we consult with the effectuall voice of the word of the Gospel. It is not left with, or to, or in our wit and endeavours to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute our selves into Christ by syllogismes, yea groundlesse syllogismes, but we waiting on the Gospel Christ effectually draws us, and takes us into himself. Sure enough Christ dyed for that soul that hangs upon this breast of the Gospel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out separation, that <hi>Christ dyed for sinners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> No man living under the sound of the Gospel, can have any true and just reason of standing still, or standing off, from coming to Christ.</head>
               <p>IF Christ open his heart so freely, and spread his arms so wide, as <hi>to receive all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rs unto him;</hi> then why do not all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117321:17"/> that hear this come to him? There are too many if God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed (as we may say after the manner of men) left among the Heathens without the bounds of the Gospel, to perish as <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates.</hi> We that are within the sound of such invitations, as the text, &amp;c. should conclude, that they do as surely, and directly belong to us, as they are spoken to us. And that we are as clearly included within the generalitie of the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions made to us; as undoubtedly they do not in the least expression exclude us. Why then should we exclude our selves? what can we scruple, or object, but here it is fully answered? Doest question whether thou mayest be so bold as to present thy self before Christ for mercie? lo Christ <hi>offers himself.</hi> The King woes the begger. <hi>We as embassadors for Christ, beseech you to be reconciled.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Doest doubt whether he means thee? See Christ most <hi>fully</hi> holds forth himself to thee. As fully, as to the thousands of souls that are now in heaven by the same Gospel-promises. <hi>What shall I do more to my vineyard?</hi> We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prescribe what more God should say, and speak, so as to Juit with a speech made to all that ever shall hear the Gospel. But sayest thou, are there not conditions on my part, which I am not able to perform? No, it is said he holds forth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self most <hi>freely.</hi> If any condition be included in coming, he works it in the Ministery that bids us come. Its a Gospel-creating word. So all comes freely to us. You have beside the free consent of the Bridegrome, the Bride, and the orderer and master of the wedding feast, and of all the friends of the Bridegrome. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Christ</hi> saith (for it is his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation to <hi>John,</hi> Chap. 1.1.) <hi>Come,</hi> in all those <hi>comes</hi> there. None could speak that, unlesse Christ first spake it. And the <hi>Spirit</hi> (the <hi>Architriclinus:</hi> that Master of the feast) saith, <hi>Come.</hi> And the <hi>Bride,</hi> the Churches, all the Saints converted, out of their own sweet experience of coming to Christ say, <hi>Come.</hi> And let <hi>him that heareth,</hi> every <hi>Minister</hi> that hears the Church says so, that hath his commission or call from Christ by the Church, saying, <hi>Come.</hi> And what do they all say? <hi>Let him that is athirst, come.</hi> If thou hast a will, doubt not of Christs will. His impression of willingnesse on thy will, is a sealed expression
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117321:17"/> of his willingnesse. And what more? And <hi>whosoever will</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an hungring will, or a wishing will, or a woulding will, so that he <hi>will</hi>) let him take of the waters of life <hi>freely.</hi> He freely gives <hi>freely</hi> offers, <hi>freely</hi> invites, therefore freely, freely, freely may he take. Thou canst name <hi>no Case of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to keep thee off, that hast a will to come; or comest (if it be possible) without a will. <hi>Him that cometh</hi> (saith Christ) I will in <hi>no wise,</hi> in <hi>no case</hi> cast out. Thou canst not imagine any sin, if thou comest to Christ, that can keep thee off. He doth not onely swear, (and Christ cannot be perjured) that inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely <hi>he desires not the death of a sinner.</hi> Ezek. 33.11. but he saith more fully, <hi>viz:</hi> universally, <hi>He is not willing that ANY should perish.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. Not <hi>blasphemous</hi> or <hi>persecuters,</hi> for he called <hi>Paul.</hi> Not <hi>murtherers,</hi> nor <hi>fornicators,</hi> nor <hi>idolaters,</hi> nor <hi>effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> nor <hi>Sodomites,</hi> nor <hi>theeves,</hi> nor <hi>covetous,</hi> nor <hi>drunkards,</hi> nor <hi>revilers,</hi> nor <hi>extortioners,</hi> for such had been some of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> but God justified and sanctified them. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. Nor such as have been <hi>possessed with the devil;</hi> for Christ called and accepted of <hi>Mary Magdalene;</hi> nor such as have been <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers,</hi> for to such also hath Christ given repentance. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.19. So that if any stand out, and not come to Christ, <hi>Thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction is of thy self O man;</hi> as God said to <hi>Israel.</hi> To them under the Gospel this is the rule. All men by the least sin are <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Eves</hi> desiring-look on the apple, the Angels first evil thought cast them out of their blessed condition: But man by the greatest sin that is, is not <hi>damned,</hi> unlesse this be added, that he comes not to Christ. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. often.</p>
               <p>Therefore why, O ye sons of men, stand ye still in a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable-mistaken-doubting condition, so as not to come to Christ? <hi>Why will ye dye?</hi> Ezek. 18. you need not perish, unlesse you will perish; no reason in Christs will, but in your will. <hi>To him that hath shall be given.</hi> You never improve the least gift to go onward towards Christ, but he prospers it to more. What would you have more, then a Christ suffering, a Christ offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a Christ intreating that you may come. Yea, (that all pretences may be removed) a Christ interceding that you may come, and beleeve. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. <hi>Neither pray I for these alone,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:117321:18"/> (meaning his disciples that then beleeved on him) but <hi>for them also which shall beleeve on me through their word;</hi> that is, through the preaching of the Gospel by his disciples, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Apostles, and Evangelists, &amp;c. to the end of the world. This intercession of Christ is called a saving to the <hi>uttermost them that come to him. Because he ever liveth to make intercession for them.</hi> So that whereas if the death and resurrection of Christ be propounded for our salvation, we may say, those are done and past, and we are not the better, or if the word &amp; prayer, and other ordinances be urged to us, as still in doing, we may say, those are weak, and do not over-power our spirits; the Apostle puts an emphasis on Christs intercession, to shew its eminencie to answer to both these replyes. 1. That <hi>he ever liveth to make intercession for them that come;</hi> so that this is still in doing, to make his death and resurrection that are past and done, still to be in force, and of efficacy. 2. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ordinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es may seem weak, his intercession <hi>saveth to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost them▪ that come;</hi> to obtain a power on ordinances to save, and to make up what is wanting in them.</p>
               <p>But to return to the point in hand, to carry on our designe, of carrying thee, O sinner, home to Christ. Out of the mouth of this point proceeds Answers to all objections; satisfaction to all scruples, removall of all obstructions; and a discovery of all disputes against it to be but pretences. Let any man but weigh Christs words and method in relation to the text and point in hand, and let him object and dispute any thing to purpose if he can. <hi>Christ</hi> in that <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. (a notable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, and sutable place to the text) having in the former part of that book set forth by great promises, and glorious representations that he will <hi>come,</hi> to make men <hi>Saints,</hi> and Saints to be a <hi>glorious universall Church;</hi> in the close (in the said <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.) he proclaims, that men should meet him in their desires for the designe in hand, saying, <hi>Let men say, Come;</hi> not onely the spirituall Spouse, but <hi>he</hi> (whosoever he be) <hi>that heareth,</hi> says, <hi>Come,</hi> and then presently Christ ecchoes, resounds twise to those two, <hi>Let him that thirsteth, come; let him that will, come:</hi> most sutable to the text. If thou doest not keep out
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117321:18"/> (whosoever thou art) <hi>Christ will not cast thee out.</hi> And therefore that of the Prophet may fitly be here applyed, <hi>Thy destruction is of thy self O Israel.</hi> For <hi>the Lord is not willing that any should pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish:</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. And he doth not onely <hi>say</hi> so, who cannot lye, (<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.) but <hi>swears</hi> so, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11.) who cannot be perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>As I live, saith the Lord, I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e not the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of a sinner.</hi> He swears by the choicest attribute, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> life,</hi> that is the root of all others, and the excellencie of his being; and therefore carries a great deal of weight with it, that in good earnest and most cordially God is not willing that any should perish, should dye eternally. Not <hi>blasphemers</hi> (to give some instances) or <hi>persecuters,</hi> see in the calling of <hi>Paul.</hi> Not <hi>murtherers,</hi> see in the conversion of <hi>Manasses.</hi> Not adulterers, or those prevailed on by the devil, see in the taking of <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> into grace and favour. All the least sins in themselves are <hi>damnable</hi> (the angels are damned for their first evil thoughts they had in heaven.) But the greatest sinners under the Gospel are not <hi>damned,</hi> unlesse they adde this, they slight the offer of Christ, and do not beleeve in him: <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. oft. Why therefore, I say again, O ye sons of men, stand ye still in a damnable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not chme in to Christ? why do you make any stay in a mistaken, doubting condition, and do not throw away all, and throw your selves upon your Saviour? The Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands with much earnestnesse (in that <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31.) <hi>Why will ye dye G house of Israel?</hi> can ye shew, can ye imagine any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son? you need not perish, unlesse you <hi>will need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> perish. There is no reason in God, but in your wils. All this that place holds forth. And therefore still I cry O sinners, what would you have more? you have a Christ that hath suffered for you; you have a Christ that hath offered himself to you; a God that hath sent him to you; a God that invites you to him; and if you <hi>come,</hi> you shall not be disappointed, saith the text. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. Though you may put many cases, yet Christ saith, <hi>In no wise will he keep you out.</hi> All which so fully and freely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the minde of God in Christ to poore sinners, as that nothing more can be said; as <hi>Isa.</hi> 5.4. <hi>What could have been done more unto my vineyard, that I have not done?</hi> And <hi>Hos.</hi> 6.4.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117321:19"/>
                  <hi>O Ephraim, what shall I do unto thee? O Judah, what shall I do unto thee?</hi> Consider now O sinner, look about thee, God acquits himself; therefore the fault must lye in thee. If thou doest im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove what thou hast, <hi>To him that hath, shall be given.</hi> Though Gods will doth not depend on mans, yet God will be tyed to his own engagement, and do as he hath said.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Profane men may and must come in to Christ, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing former presumptions and despairs.</head>
               <p>YEt for all the text and point in hand, many stand off, dispute, cavil, and come not in to Christ: As, 1. Profane men; 2. Hipocriticall professors. 3. Embrions, that is, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or new-conceptions of Christianity, but not yet shaped, and formed to maturitie of a compleat birth. But the point in hand well managed will confute them all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Profane men</hi> stand out upon two extreames. 1. Presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. 2. Despair. And <hi>this</hi> usually follows <hi>that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Upon <hi>presumption.</hi> And why? they can (as they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatively think) do well enough without Christ. For they seek not after him. But if this were true, why then did Christ coming into the world, make this proposition, this offer of himself to you? It seems Christ well knows you have dear need of him. Yea and you (profane men) seem also some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to know that you need some such things as a <hi>Christ.</hi> For else, while you are out of Christ, why doth your consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence somtimes, for some sins give you some short and sharp bitings? why do you in your afflictions, or when you are (as you think) upon your dying pillow, so oft repeat these words, <hi>For Christs sake, O for Christ his sake?</hi> sure you think that God cannot in justice save you without satisfaction; That Christ did not dye in vain, namely, there was need of him for such as you are. That Christ did not speak and pen this text in vain, but for your necessity. If you reply, you have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117321:19"/> Christ, for you professe him, and beleeve his word to be true; we must needs then <hi>quaere</hi> with you, how can you be said tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have Christ, and really live in your profanesse? have you Christ, and are ye lyars too? have you Christ, and are ye swearers too? Is Christ a profane Christ? If not; how shall Christ and the Belials of wickednesses dwell together?</p>
               <p>If you object, no man is without sin; We answer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he that is truly in Christ, is without a <hi>will</hi> to sin. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8, 9. He cannot yeeld with a <hi>full will</hi> to sin. There is a strong inward reluctation against it. 2. That he is without <hi>grosse sins</hi> in practise. 3. Without a <hi>custome</hi> in any known sin. 4. He continually <hi>goes to Christ</hi> to be more sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and so should you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Despair</hi> sometimes keep men off from Christ. When the devil cannot keep them off in one extreame, then he labours to keep them off in another. And for this purpose he arms them with many unreasonable objections.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. Saith the Despairer, my sins are too many, too great, of too long continuance to be pardoned by Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> If this were true, why doth not Christ make this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in the text? Doth he not say just the contrary, that <hi>him that cometh to him, he will in NO WISE cast out?</hi> Hath he any where excluded sins, because <hi>many</hi> or <hi>great,</hi> or of <hi>long</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance from pardon, whiles he offers it in the ordinances? Is not Christ true, and able, and willing to make good his word? Is there any sin <hi>thou</hi> hast committed which he hath not pardoned to another? might not <hi>Judas</hi> his sin have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, had he come to Christ, as well as others committing the same sin? <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36. Sure when he saith, <hi>In no wise will he cast out any that come to him,</hi> he hath an unlimited satisfaction for, &amp; compassion to all sorts of sinners, in all sorts of sin <hi>that come to him.</hi> As <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1, &amp;c. <hi>If any thirst, if any will call upon him, seek to him, lay aside his own thoughts, and hearken to Christs,</hi> he will <hi>have mercy,</hi> to take away all <hi>sorts</hi> of sinfull miseries; he <hi>will abundantly pardon</hi> (or as it is in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> he will <hi>multiply to pardon,</hi> to take away the <hi>numerousnesse</hi> of sins. And <hi>his thoughts are</hi> (he saith) <hi>above our thoughts, as high as the heavens are above
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117321:20"/> the earth,</hi> to take away the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of sins. And he will <hi>make his word effectuall, as the rain upon the earth</hi> to stop the <hi>continuance</hi> of sin. For indeed his mercy is infinite, as well in <hi>perpetuitie</hi> as <hi>immensitie.</hi> And all such high, and comprehensive expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of mercy, are more expresly and particularly entailed on such a bleeding heart as thine is, as Chirurgions most look to the most broken, and wounded. <hi>Isa.</hi> 66.2. <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18, 19. look these places in the said quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and consider them. If thou be wounded indeed in spirit, thou wilt turn to them, and study them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Saith the despairer, I have so many, and so great afflictions, that God seems to signifie to me by them, that he means to damne me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> This is no good argument. For if it had; then Christ would not have said without limitation, <hi>Him that cometh to me I will in no wise cast out;</hi> be his afflictions never so many or great, or grim in shew of signification. For indeed no man can conclude God <hi>hates him,</hi> by his affliction. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 9.1. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may conclude from his affliction, that God <hi>loves him.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.7. And that to have no affliction, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a signe of Gods hate. <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. But saith the despairer, God hath forsaken me. I cannot pray, I cannot hear as sometimes I could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> The text doth not run upon those terms of <hi>so</hi> praying, or <hi>so</hi> hearing; or whether thou didst pray or hear formerly. The question is, whether thou doest now by praying, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any how so look after Christ as now to <hi>come,</hi> now to scrabble to him, to sigh for him, to be restlesse for him? such a one <hi>Christ will in no wise cast out.</hi> And for his forsaking thee; God usually doth never forsake man <hi>remedilesly,</hi> till he forsake him with <hi>refusing of the remedie.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.15, 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1. If by forsaking thou meanest a temporary par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall forsaking, which we call <hi>desertion,</hi> that is, a withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of assistance, and inward feeling of comfort; this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of desertion simply in it self is not sinfull: for Christ was in it. However God withdraws, in case thou perceivest it, complainest of it, grievest for it (as thy objection is here)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117321:20"/> this may be in godly persons: <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.17. say the Saints there, <hi>O Lord why hast thou made us to erre from thy wayes, and hardned our hearts from thy fear?</hi> And yet in the verse before they say to the Lord, <hi>Doubtlesse thou art our Father;</hi> and in the close of the 17. verse, they pray earnestly to the Lord to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</hi> So they that <hi>fear the Lord may be in darknesse, and see no light.</hi> Isa. 50.10. And godly <hi>Jonah</hi> said, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.4. <hi>I am cast out of thy sight.</hi> So <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 22.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. But saith the despairing despondent soul, I am afraid I have sinned the sin against the holy Ghost.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> 1. If as in that text, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. thou <hi>comest,</hi> thou hast not sinned the sin against the holy Ghost; yea thou canst not (as thou saiest in the objection) be <hi>afraid</hi> thou hast sinned it, if thou hast sinned it. For the sin against the holy Ghost is to be impenitently at defiance with the grace of Christ.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The sin against the holy Ghost, is not to have or act sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and unworthy thoughts or deeds against the Godhead of the holy Spirit. For then so to sin against God the Father (as God in pure essence of the deitie) or against Christ (as God incarnate) were unpardonable; which the Scripture doth not affirm. 2. It is not to sin in thoughts, words or deeds against the holy Spirit, meerly as it denotes in generall, the manner or way of Gods giving forth himself operatively in spirituall effects; then every sin against knowledge were the sin against the holy Ghost, which is not so. But the sin against the holy Ghost is against the efficacy of it in us. As when a man hath been inlightned, and convinced of the truth of the word by the Spirit, and yet doth impenitently maligne, and maliciously oppose this truth in others, contrary to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions on his own heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117321:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Hypocriticall professors, the self-deceiving Christians may, and must come in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Christ, and not make a stand any <hi>where,</hi> or at any <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that is short of Christ, though it hath never so fair a shew of salvation.</head>
               <p n="2">2. FAlse professors, unsound Christians seem to look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Christ▪ yea as it were to move towards him, but by reason of severall mistakes, they make severall stops at somewhat that is not Christ, and so stand off, short of Christ. These are to be dealt with in this Chapter, and to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and brought off from their mistakes, and to be drawn home to Christ himself by vertue of the text, and point in hand: which holds forth Christ himself personally, <hi>Him that comes to ME,</hi> I will <hi>in no wise east out.</hi> We must still be <hi>coming,</hi> and coming till we come to <hi>Him himself,</hi> or else all will be in vain.</p>
               <p>For as Christ in himself is the best thing God hath in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in earth; so he is the best thing that can be had for thee sinner (of what sort soever thou art) for he is <hi>God manifested in the flesh,</hi> the <hi>Godhead dwelling bodily, Immanuel God with us:</hi> (as the Scripture tels us) so that there is nothing in Religion comparable to him, to invite thee, allure thee, and stay thee there, from him; without whom all Religion is but husks. To come to particulars: The condition of the mistaking pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor, is like a man in a palace, going up a stately payer of stairs to speak (as he pretends) with the King. He steps up one step and there meets with the <hi>yeaman of the guard</hi> and takes him for the King, talks with him, and makes a great stay there. Anon perceiving that that is not the King, he steps a step higher, and there he meets with one of the Kings <hi>Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,</hi> and here makes a stand as before. A while after, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this not to be the King, he steps a step higher, &amp; meets with the <hi>Secretary of State,</hi> then a step higher, and meets with <hi>one of the Kings Bed-chamber,</hi> then a step higher, and meets with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117321:21"/> the <hi>Prince</hi> that came out of the loins of the King, and still takes all these for the King, makes a stand to tarry with every one of them, but all this while comes not to the king himself. So the mistaking Christian stops at every thing in Religion, that is not Christ. If he go on, it is but to something that is a greater shew of Christ, or to somewhat that is neerer in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Christ, but not to Christ himself. Now the businesse in the insuing Sections of this Chapter is to undeceive these dreaming doting professors in all particulars, and draw them into the Chamber of Presence to the King himself, to Christ himself.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECTION I.</hi> RESTRAINT from sin is not a taking of Christ.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THis hypocrite, or false professor, weighing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the ugly garbe and foule behaviour of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boshtnesse, profanesse, and scandalousnesse of life, as odious to God and men, his naturall conscience pricks him forward to go one step beyond that; and therefore he sets forth in his own morall strength of humane reasonings, and resolutions, stirred by civill considerations and ends to forbear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain himself from outward grosse evils. Having thus done, here he stays as if he had met with Christ, or that which is as good as a Christ, so contented is he, applauding his own condition in his own heart, like the Pharisees that gloried in <hi>making clean the outside of the cup and platter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But O thou poore blinde soul, this is not Christ, nor salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Christ. Thou art not yet come to Christ, and so not to any thing saving that is in or from Christ. The text and point in hand do indeed invite thee <hi>from</hi> all evil; but then to <hi>come to Christ</hi> himself. Forbearance of evil is a kinde of <hi>guard</hi> about a man, that he be not entangled with grosse evils to hinder him from Christ. But the <hi>guard</hi> is not the King. Those whom Christ invites here, were generally those that were free from grosse offences, as Scribes and Pharisees, but these
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117321:22"/> Christ cals <hi>hypocrites,</hi> six or seven times in one Chapter, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. and moralized Jews; all which yet for all that he invites to <hi>come to him,</hi> and he will not <hi>cast them out.</hi> Intimating that they were not by outward morall honesty in a safe estate, but were yet <hi>without</hi> till they <hi>come</hi> home to <hi>him.</hi> Being come to Christ, thou goest beyond any condition an unregenerate man may be found in, either of <hi>restraining</hi> grace, <hi>humbling</hi> grace, or outward reformation. For an <hi>Abimilech,</hi> or <hi>Laban</hi> may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> restrained from sin. A <hi>Cain,</hi> an <hi>Esau,</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> may be cast down with some kinde of humiliation. An <hi>Herod,</hi> and a <hi>Pharisee</hi> may <hi>do many good things.</hi> Therefore for thee to stand off in this condition, is to stand but in their condition; but to come to Christ puts thee beyond all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: II.</hi> Bare performance of DƲTIES is not a taking of Christ.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. IF this mistaken false professor be by divine providence often afrighted in this condition, and so sees that still he is in an unsafe condition; then out of self-love for his own security, he steps a 2d: step further, and higher, and fals up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on much performance of duty, as hearing, praying, fasting, &amp;c. But here is the mistake, and the making the stand: that he thinks that by these performances to hammer out a sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to himself. Yea makes these his <hi>Christ,</hi> as the <hi>Papists</hi> do the <hi>number</hi> of their prayers and fastings. And the <hi>Pharisees</hi> did their outward performance and observations of their enlarged <hi>phylactaries,</hi> parchments of morall traditions.</p>
                  <p>But, O poore soul, still hearken to the text and point, that thou must <hi>come to Christ.</hi> Thou must come to him to take him in, and by performances; not to stand off, and make a stay in duties from Christ, to love the duty and not apply Christ; to rest in the performance, rather then to trust in Christ; to make perhaps a sound of Christ, but not have a sence an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> feeling of Christ in thee: rather naming Christ for the dutie sake, then to do the duty for Christs sake. And therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minde it O poore soul, that to stay in performances, is but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117321:22"/> to do as the Kings <hi>Pensioner,</hi> stand at the doore in attendance with a lance or, &amp;c. but is not in the roome with the King. Minde it, minde it, thou must in and through all duties and performances come to Christ, as the summe, and end, and perfection of all. So the text: so <hi>John</hi> 5.39, 40. If men never so much <hi>search the Scriptures,</hi> and do <hi>in them think to finde eternall life,</hi> yet if they do not consider them as <hi>testifying of Christ,</hi> and so by them <hi>come to Christ,</hi> they cannot <hi>be saved.</hi> A place, and thing much to be weighed. And therefore to stand off in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under a generall notion and conceit, that this is the way to please God, and not distinctly to minde that this is onely the <hi>way</hi> to Christ, and not minde and intend this as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe, it is the way neither to please God, nor to come to Christ, nor to appease their own unquiet heart, but the ready course to obstruct and hinder all three. In this way of toyling in ordinances thou hast onely thy labour for thy travaile; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious working in this way becomes not a reward, but a drudgerie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: III.</hi> Common GRACES are not Christ.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. AFter a while perhaps this mistaken creature being wearied with his pains-taking in performances, by reason that he finds no inward comfort, he perceives no oyl to come out of these flints, he casts about, and hearing of a thing called <hi>grace,</hi> he steps a 3d: step higher, and never rests till he hath attained to some common graces, of illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conviction, legall humiliations, &amp;c. and with these dresseth forth his profession to some plausible trimnesse, to talk reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously, to confer with good Ministers, to company with some of the best professors.</p>
                  <p>But here is thy miserable mistake, poor soul, that here again thou stoppest, as if thou hadst somewhat of Christ, and so dost not come to Christ himself. Thou hast met with the <hi>Secretary</hi> that doth somewhat set forth what the King is, but thou hast not the King himself. Therefore heed it, heed it, that the text
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117321:23"/> and point do not invite thee meerly to some retinue of Christ, but to Christ himself, Common graces, outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and religious priviledges do tell thee (as <hi>John</hi> the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptist speaks of himself) they are not <hi>the Christ,</hi> they confesse, and deny it not, that they are those that onely cry, <hi>Prepare ye the way of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. and that the <hi>Kingdom of heaven is at hand;</hi> that there <hi>is one that coms after us to be preferred afore us;</hi> that he must <hi>increase,</hi> and <hi>we decrease</hi> in that thine opinion &amp; esteem. Be not therefore undone in a pleasant dream, as the foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ish virgins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.1, &amp;c. that went ten degrees beyond the profane; in <hi>name virgins,</hi> in <hi>company</hi> keep <hi>with the wise,</hi> in <hi>blaze of</hi> profession had lamps in sitting in the <hi>Kingdome of heaven of ordinances,</hi> in generall <hi>notions of Christ,</hi> some <hi>expectation</hi> and <hi>waiting for Christ,</hi> in some <hi>skill to distinguish the noyse of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> in some <hi>preparations</hi> for him, <hi>they went about to trim their lamps,</hi> they in a sort <hi>go out to meet Christ;</hi> but they fall short neer ten degrees of the wise; for it was not with them as with the wise; to have the <hi>Kingdom of ordinances within them,</hi> (as Christ saith, <hi>The Kingdom of God is within you</hi>) to <hi>be wise,</hi> not onely to be <hi>with the wise,</hi> to see all <hi>safe</hi> afore they be <hi>secure;</hi> to <hi>have oyl in their vessels,</hi> the anointing of the Spirit of faith in the heart, to <hi>unite to Christ</hi> (the principall verb, the main of all,) to be <hi>sensible of wants afore it</hi> be too late; to look to ones own spirituall <hi>provisions,</hi> and not to relye on borrowing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as to think to go to heaven by others goodnesse, or outward priviledges, to <hi>enter in</hi> with Christ by vertue of <hi>oyl in the vessell,</hi> faith applying Christ; not to <hi>relye upon bare prayer and words, Lord, Lord,</hi> without urging any <hi>divine interest.</hi> To be <hi>known and acknowledged of Christ,</hi> by inward perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heart by faith, as well as to know Christ. To <hi>have the oyl of grace</hi> that will hold out to the last, &amp;c. You see here the losse of Christ, is the losse of all. And sure enough those graces, those actings, those performances that are from, and stirred by Christ, will tend to Christ, send us to Christ.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:117321:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IIII.</hi> Brain knowledge of promises is not reall taking of Christ.</head>
                  <p n="4">4. IN processe of time this self-deceiving soul hearing such a noise in the ministery of the word <hi>of Christ,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving that Christ dyed for sinners,</hi> he steps and ascends another step higher, so as to have some <hi>promises</hi> whereby to believe that Christ dyed for sinners; and when he hath one or two of these to settle his judgement that Christ dyed for sinners, when he hath got these tidings into his head, he thinks he hath Christ, and there he staies; too long. But O soul to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, come on further yet. There is a wide difference between coming <hi>to a promise,</hi> and coming to Christ through a promise: promises are of the <hi>Kings</hi> Bed-chamber, but are not the <hi>King.</hi> The text is a promise, a precious one; but we are not onely to come to the sound of that, and receive the sence of that into the head, but we are invited by it to come to <hi>Christ himself.</hi> The stony ground catcht the promise, and ran away with it with joy, but took not <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> though he suffered with him, and for him. And thou poore soul, thou doest not take the promise as a ticket or warrant from God the Father to challenge and own Christ, and therein to have the full truth and substance of the promise (as it is said notably, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.) But thou takest the promises as the <hi>history</hi> of Christ cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, neglecting to apply the <hi>mystery</hi> of Christ crucified to thy self, as thine, as if crucified for thee, if for no other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. V.</hi> A RESOLƲTION upon our own STRENGTH to beleeve in Christ, is an hindrance of coming to Christ.</head>
                  <p n="5">5. THerefore this poore deceived soul, finding by some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the decay of his sudden joy, &amp; how deeply he is oft plunged in sorrows, and fear by every affliction, he thinks (upon further information) that he must step one step higher, and that is to take Christ, and rest upon him by faith.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117321:24"/>
                  <p>But here is thy sad mistake O poor soul, that yet keeps thee from Christ, that thou thinkest to do this by thine own strength. Faith indeed is the <hi>Prince,</hi> but it is born from the loynes of Christ. That faith that gives Christ, is given of God through Christ, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.8. The <hi>text</hi> saith, thou must <hi>come to Christ,</hi> meaning, that effectually thou comest by <hi>faith;</hi> but then it is in the <hi>context,</hi> thou canst not come, unlesse <hi>God the Father draw thee.</hi> Yea <hi>Christ must draw</hi> thee: <hi>Cant.</hi> 1:4. It is he that speaketh to thee to come, must make thee by that word (spirited) to come. Thou must as well wait on the word to be wrought to a faith in Christ, as to look upon that word to be directed and invited to come. Thou must not think to believe by thine own power or resolution. It must be the same God that gives Christ to thee, to give thy heart to Christ. And so thou art to wait on the same God in the same promises to give unto thee both light and life, will &amp; power, to lay hold on Christ. Thou must consider that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Christ hath purchased by his death and resurrection a pardon for thy soul, so by the same he hath purchased Gods efficacy to bring thee in to him by faith. And therefore thou doest <hi>obtrude</hi> thy self, and art an <hi>intruder,</hi> if thou goest to Christ in thine own strength. It is true, no man coming to Christ can be said to be an intruder upon Christ, as if Christ were not extended to him; or that he came too soon, or was too forward to be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him, for according to the texts indefinitenesse, and unlimitednes, none (without exception) can come too much, or come too soon to Christ to be welcome. But if thou come in thine own power to believe, bearing thy self up upon thine own rationall considerations, and peremtorie resolutions, that thou wilt believe, because thou wilt believe; then thou doest plainly <hi>obtrude</hi> thy self on Christ, art an <hi>intruder</hi> upon salvation. So that if you wilt avoid this imputation, thou must fix the eye of thy expectation on God, to give Christ to thee, and to see the free and kinde gift, and by Christs Spirit as the only efficacie to work faith in thee to receive him. And then come and welcome Fly not off as they, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.65▪ 66. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Christ saith, <hi>None can come to him, except God the Father draw him:</hi> but therefore the rather come on, seek that power
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117321:24"/> of God; it is to be had, and it will do the thing; thy power is nothing; or if any thing, it will not do the deed. Christ saith in the context, we that come are <hi>given to Christ.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 65. <hi>that it is given</hi> to us of God to come to Christ. It should seem both are intended for a gift; and therefore God will give them. <hi>Ask and have. And if you that are evill can give good things to your children, how much more will God give the Spirit to them that ask it?</hi> When Christ saith in the text emphatically <hi>I,</hi> even <hi>I</hi> will in no wise cast out, he means that <hi>He,</hi> even he must <hi>receive in.</hi> As he saith, <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.11.25. <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy transgressions for my own sake. I, even I, am the Lord, and beside me there is no Saviour.</hi> God in Christ is all in all in satisfaction, and in efficacie. We come to the <hi>Bethesda</hi> of ordinances; but Christ the <hi>Angel of his presence,</hi> (as <hi>Isaiah</hi> cals him) stirs the waters.</p>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAGRAPH I.</hi> A soul must not come towards Christ, but for Christ himself.</head>
                     <p>IN summe, the text holds forth a right coming to Christ upon the designe of beleeving, to consist in two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hings. 1. That a poor soul must not come for any by end but for <hi>Christ,</hi> for the excellency of Christ, to have Christ, <hi>Him that cometh to ME,</hi> saith the text, that is, to have <hi>me,</hi> desire <hi>me</hi> for my <hi>self.</hi> A man comes not of meer necessity, and self-love, to avoid something that is not Christ, as <hi>hell,</hi> or the like; but is drawn with the amiablenesse of Christs excellencie. That if there were no <hi>Hell</hi> of <hi>torment,</hi> yet he would prize Christs excellency to deliver him from the <hi>hell of sin,</hi> that is, the <hi>power, filth, and vexation</hi> of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAGRAPH II.</hi> A s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul sincerely coming to Christ, feels and tasts something of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he seems to come at him.</head>
                     <p n="2">2. THat a poore soul coming towards Christ, finds his heart drawn with some inward motions and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117321:25"/> of Christ on it, in the way of inward content, and more satisfaction of spirit whiles he is coming, and making to Christ then ever before. Though as yet he cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Christ, grasp him in his arms; yet he feels, while he is coming, a swetnes ore-flowing his spirit; and his good hope, that one day he shall have him more fully, is a great soul-sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and quietation of his spirit the mean while</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG. III.</hi> We must come to ordinances, duties, &amp;c. but through them to Christ.</head>
                     <p>UPon all that hath been said, let the poore soul observe two directions. That though any real coming towards, or looking for Christ in the ordinances, be a part of the meaning of the text; yet</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Let him not take hold of any thing, but of Christ, or in relation to Christ. Rest in nothing but him. But be coming to him, in as many ordinances, duties, performances as thou wilt. O consider that the sins of men do not more displease Christ (if so much) as their falling in love with the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids of Christ, more then with Christ himself; with any thing that leads to Christ, to loyter there instead of coming and abiding with Christ.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: IIII.</hi> We must take whole Christ.</head>
                     <p n="2">2. AS he must not contentedly lye in a state of sin; so not to be contented with the preparations to, or peeces of Christ (as a man is wont to think he may carve this or that of Christ to himself, and leave the rest) but to desire &amp; reach after <hi>totum Christum, &amp; totum Christi.</hi> Somewhat of all in Christ, and of all that thou maiest have in Christ, in this life.</p>
                     <p>I say, stay not in <hi>preparations</hi> to Christ: as in <hi>humiliations.</hi> It is not said by Christ, <hi>Him that is weary and heavy laden I will ease:</hi> But <hi>him that is weary and heavy laden, if he COME to me, I will ease. Matth.</hi> 11.28.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:117321:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The <hi>embryon professors,</hi> those that are but a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of, or a reall disposition to Christianitie; for all their fearing, whining, pining and complaining, may, and must come in to Christ.</head>
               <p>THe 3d: sort that stand off too much, and do not come roundly and fully on to Christ, are the <hi>embryon</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. That is, such as in whom there is young conception of, or reall disposition to true good in them, but we can hardly say they are a new <hi>birth.</hi> Or if we may say they are <hi>in the birth;</hi> we cannot well say they are <hi>actually born;</hi> but lye in the very <hi>birth,</hi> they have more pain then pleasure spiritually. They are as in a swown or transe; they do not know how it is with them; but sprawl and struggle for life. We have oft instances of such Christians as these in the world; they dare not go back to <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet go not forward cheerily towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> but stand as in a wildernes complaining. They dare not return to sin, and they dare not boldly to claim Christ; and so stand weeping as in the valley of <hi>Bacha</hi> between both. Yea they cannot part with Christ, and yet they are afraid to take him. They are like a man fallen into the Sea, a ship coming by, he catcheth hold, is towed and drawn after it, hanging onely on the out-side, he dares not let go, lest he be drowned; and he dares not climbe up into it, lest he should misse of his purpose. These Christians I speak of, are in some degree the <hi>smoaking flax (Matth.</hi> 12.) they have some weak soul-ascendings like pillars of smoak, up from the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this sinfull world (<hi>Cant.</hi> 3.6.) when no flaming or fire of graces appear to give clear light and sight, what is in them. They are as babes that cry for milk, yet the brest drops into their mouth, cry still and do not take the breast to suck. They have a spirituall <hi>being</hi> begun, but come not off freely to Christ for a wel-being. They cannot rest in themselves, or their present condition, yet they have not for present the art
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117321:26"/> and heart so wholly, and fully, and distinctly to rest on Christ. They stand looking out, sighing, wishing for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, and the comfort of it, but do not clearly and closely come and close with it.</p>
               <p>The lets that hinder a while this creature from coming home and wholly to Christ, are foure. He thinks,
<list>
                     <item>1. That Christ is too good for him.</item>
                     <item>2. Himself too bad for Christ.</item>
                     <item>3. The work of <hi>coming</hi> impossible for him to do.</item>
                     <item>4. Improbable for Christ to do.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>These foure are as the <hi>quaternion</hi> of souldiers that kept <hi>Peter</hi> in prison, till the Angel of the Lord came and delivered him. So spiritually. As some men have tied their own hands and feet, and then put their feet through between their arms, and so seem to have been bound hands and feet by others, when it is by themselves; so this kind of poore soul through dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and perplexity of spirit thinks other outward things hinder him from Christ, when as it is he himself that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexeth himself.</p>
               <p>All these pretended hindrances are to be removed by this point.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The first let, that Christ is too good for them REMOVED.</head>
                  <p>THese thus urge against themselves. 1. That Christ is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; holy God-man; and <hi>the pure onely shall see God;</hi> but we (say they) have no puritie. 2. Those Saints that have to do with Christ, are full of holy <hi>meditations,</hi> holy <hi>inlargements</hi> in desires and prayers, full of holy <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>gracious actings;</hi> now had we some holinesse, some graces, some inlargements in desire, and prayer, and some such gracious actings, we might with some boldnesse come to Christ.</p>
                  <p>To this the text and doctrine replies, that there is no such condition in them; Christ did never bid them speak thus conditionally; he never by them prescribed this method. But command his word to tell this sort of Christians that in this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117321:26"/> objection, you put the cart before the horse. If you could be holy afore you come to Christ, you had no need of Christ; if Gods or Christs purity should hinder coming, nor you, nor any else should be saved. The fire is made to burn that which is not fire. The Sun is appointed to shine upon the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that of it self is dark. Christ is holy, for the purpose to make the unholy to be holy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. to shine upon their darknesse, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. Is there any such clause in the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that we must be holy before we come to partake of it? N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, it doth not finde us, but makes us pure, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. The text saith not the <hi>holy</hi> that comes, but <hi>him</hi> that comes. The new Covenant finds us <hi>in our blood,</hi> not in <hi>holinesse. Ezek.</hi> 16.6. Christ blesseth them that are <hi>thirsty and poore, Matth.</hi> 5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Luk</hi> 1.53. Not the <hi>worker,</hi> but the <hi>willer</hi> is called; <hi>whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will,</hi> let him come: Not he that can greatly <hi>obey,</hi> but he that <hi>heareth. Revel.</hi> 22.17.</p>
                  <p>In old time husbands gave portions for their wives. Christ comes and buyes us with his blood, makes us rich with his grace, doth not finde us so. <hi>He that hath nothing</hi> (saith the Prophet) even let him come. The poore woman when she is woed hath nothing but her self. The poore patient hath nothing but misery to move pity, so are we at first, to Christ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> But may not a man so unholy and unworthy be said to <hi>presume,</hi> whiles he so boldly comes to Christ?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi> For a soul wholly to go out of himself, and by the promise to venture <hi>himself nakedly</hi> on <hi>naked Christ,</hi> is rather an holy <hi>despair</hi> in his own righteousnesse, then a <hi>presumption.</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>obedience</hi> to Christs invitation, then an <hi>over-boldnesse.</hi> A man will marry onely that women that will leave father and mother, &amp; trust her self with her husband, cleave to him, to go, and fare, and be where, and how he is and doth. So Christ us spiritually. The Scriptures all along speak very carefully to take us off of our selves. As <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places. The act of giving Christ to us, and of us to Christ; and conveighances, decrees, faith, ordinances, and their effectuall workings, are all of God. We are in the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall act onely <hi>passively</hi> to receive, having nothing of our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117321:27"/> selves. To the woman in debt as long as she had but vessels to receive, the oyl ran. Why art thou then so sad O soul, why so cast down? The poorer spiritually, the neerer Christ. As nothing in us coming to Christ can make us worthy of Christ: so nothing in us can make us unworthy. If any thing, sin; and he came to call <hi>not the righteous, but sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: II.</hi> The second let or hindrance that keeps off the new conception embrion Christian from throwing himself wholly on Christ, <hi>thinking himself too bad for Christ;</hi> removed.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, this embryon or young conception objects he is too bad for Christ. To which we answer, that as there are degrees of goodnesse; and accordingly a weak Christian would not onely have <hi>some</hi> goodnesse, but <hi>much</hi> goodnesse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he comes to Christ (which is impossible): so there are degrees of badnesse, and accordingly, if a little badnesse doth not dismay him, yet <hi>much</hi> doth. And thereupon, most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly he cries out, <hi>he is to bad for Christ;</hi> and so unworthy, as not fit to touch the promises. The grounds on which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth himself too bad for Christ are, 1. the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of his sins, O (saith he) my sins are great in <hi>number;</hi> more (as the Psalmist speaks) <hi>then the hairs of mine head.</hi> Or great in <hi>guilt</hi> through many and manifold aggravating circumstances. Or great in <hi>bulk,</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> sins, <hi>Psal.</hi> 51. Or great in <hi>length;</hi> an old sinner, a sinner of many yeers standing; that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most sinned away all his daies. To this ground of his obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the text and doctrine answer. <hi>Him that cometh, Christ will in no wise cast out.</hi> Him who comes off of himself, (as <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1, &amp;c.) though he hath nothing wherewith to buy any thing of Christ, yet if he will come to Christ, <hi>Him will Christ in no wise cast out.</hi> For he that most apprehends his sin in a self-detestation, is neerest to that coming off of himself. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9, 10. Men talk much of <hi>self-deniall;</hi> but here is the root, and first life-act of self-deniall,<note place="margin">The main self-denyall.</note> to deny all our own worth, and worthinesse, and to professe our needinesse of Christ. And
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117321:27"/> such Christ invites to follow him. <hi>If any man will deny himself, let him follow me.</hi> The text and doctrine thence, make no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction of greater, and lesser sins, or sinners, <hi>magis &amp; minus,</hi> more and lesse, do not alter the kinde or case.<note place="margin">Not sins small. All sins small.</note> In regard of Gods justice, Heavens joy, Hels torments, the souls excellency, there is no little sin, or small sinner. But in regard of Gods mercy, Christs satisfaction, and the power of the holy Spirit, so all sins in comparison are as nothing. For between finite, and infinite, there is no proportion. <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.8. View the place, it is a precious one. And the text and doctrine intimate, that him who is worthy to be cast out, and thinks so of himself, (for the two negatives are put to give satisfaction to great doubtings) yet <hi>HIM coming to Christ</hi> with that sight, and that appetite, that Christ hath given him by this and the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations, <hi>will Christ in no wise cast out.</hi> So the whole current of the Gospel. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. And as in these invitations Christ doth not in the least hint any difference of sinners, so nor of number of sins. If God <hi>blot out sin,</hi> meerly <hi>for his own sake, Isa.</hi> 43.25. and <hi>justifies freely by his grace;</hi> then not for the <hi>numbers</hi> sake, nor for times sake, because a man hath sinned but a little while. <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit regi:</hi> Against divine forgiving mercy no time can plead prescription. The pardon may come to one at the <hi>eleventh and last</hi> houre of the day, (as to the <hi>theefe on</hi> the Crosse) when he sees a need of Christ. This is good for meditation, after much time is past, but not before to neglect time. He sees not truly a need of Christ, that can willingly neglect him. Therefore lay aside this objection touching the greatnesse of thy sins. It may be thy sins are not now more then others, but since thou heardst of infinite mercy, and infinite satisfaction to pardon sin, thou seest more of sin, and more in sin. Thy condition is no other then what hath been the condition of other Saints, who have been troubled for the <hi>number, yea of secret</hi> sins. <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. and with the <hi>nature</hi> but of the smallest sort of sins, namely, of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscence. Rom.</hi> 7. But in case thy sins be, and thou seest them to be greater then others, what follows but this, that thou shalt the more honour God in beleeving, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.33. and hast
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117321:28"/> cause to admire Gods mercy. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</p>
                  <p>Another ground of thinking himself to be too bad for Christ, is his ungratefull slighting the means of salvation. I have (saith he) heard many Sermons, and have not been convinced. Or affected oft, but not reformed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ans.</hi> The text saith, <hi>the coming man shall not be cast out.</hi> Though he be going and coming, like a little childe playing to and fro with the parent; yet still hath more affection to stay, then to depart quite; he will be a reteiner to Christ; he hath an affection to, at least an appretiation of this master more then of others, Christ will not cast him out, Christ was willing to treat with those that were worse then this poore creature we speak of. In <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. see their badnesse, In <hi>v.</hi> 18. see Christs treaty. Yea the Church unkindly neglecting Christ, Christ stands at the doore till his locks were wet with the dew of the night. That is, he in his person did, and in his Ministers still doth suffer much opposition from men, whiles he stands woeing souls to come to him. And Christ is very patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that <hi>lukewarm</hi> and much corrupted Church <hi>Laodicea. Revel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>He stands at the doore and knocks;</hi> and if at last any <hi>open unto him, he will come in and sup with them.</hi> He will cheer them, and be cheerfull with them in their hearts. Christ in the first 9 Chapters of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> under the name of <hi>wisdom,</hi> and notion of a Suter woes souls from sin; whiles sin under the name of an <hi>harlot</hi> indeavours to woe them from him. Woers are contented if they win the affections at last.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> There is a refusall that is dangerous. <hi>Psa.</hi> 95. <hi>God sware they should not enter into his rest.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> The refusall is dangerous, if it be long, and also obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as in that 95. <hi>Psalm,</hi> compare 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.15, 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1. But if a soul hath some remorse, and meltings of heart after the Lord Christ; his beams have been upon that heart, and will ere long appear. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2. <hi>The house of Israel lamented after the Lord.</hi> They put away their idols, <hi>Samuel</hi> prayes for them, and the Lord shewed favour to them. In all those Psalms, wherein <hi>David pants after God, as the Hart after the water</hi> brooks, and his <hi>heart thirsts after him;</hi> God ere
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117321:28"/> the Psalm be at an end, manifests himself to <hi>Davids</hi> soul. The Spouse, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. having sent Christ away with her neglect of him, and after seeking of him, being sick of love for him, in Chap. 6. she sweetly finds him. Adde to all, <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.4, 5. <hi>I will heal</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>their back-slidings, and love them freely, I will be as a dew to Israel, he shall grow up as the lily, and cast forth his roots as Lebanon.</hi> Though we have our back-slidings, yet God hath his pursuings after us, and his healings for us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT: III. 3d: Let or hindrance that keeps the poore young conception from full closing with Christ, <hi>thinking it impossible for him to come to Christ</hi> removed.</head>
                  <p>I Have, saith he, neither will nor power either to do, or to be humbled for not doing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. Concerning <hi>will</hi> thus. God shews mercy first, and originally, not because <hi>thou</hi> hast a will, but because <hi>he</hi> hath a will. <hi>He will have mercy, on whom he will have mercy. Rom.</hi> 9.15, 16. Yea the text is plain, <hi>All that the Father gives to Christ shall come to him.</hi> Adde <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and passeth by the transgression of the remnant of his heritage▪ he retaineth not HIS ANGER FOR EVER, because he DELIGHTETH IN MERCY?</hi> See here the ample ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of his mercy, and the originall cause of it, namely, in him himself, not in thee. God sheweth mercy directly, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and intentionally. So that <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. But he execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth judgement as it were accidentally, occasionally, and consequentially, in case that men refuse mercy, first offered to them. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.13, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 15. Again we answer further. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God of his own free will hath cast his love upon us, and from that originall writes a copy in our hearts to be willing to imbrace his love; in this, <hi>It is he that works in us to will, and to do of his good pleasure. Phil.</hi> 2.13. It is said, <hi>All shall work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good to them that love God. Rom.</hi> 8. And how come we to love him? <hi>John</hi> shews us. 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> Ch. 4. <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>We love him, because
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117321:29"/> he loved us first.</hi> It is a plain signe of a will in us to believe, and receive Christ, when we wait upon God alone to work on that will in us. So the man in the Gospel: <hi>Lord I believe, help mine unbelief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning <hi>power,</hi> our Answer is this. The text and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth not say, him that cometh by his own power, shall not be cast out, but him that cometh, though by anothers power, namely, by the <hi>gift of the Father.</hi> So <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. <hi>Ye are saved by grace, through faith, and that</hi> (to wit, that faith) <hi>is not of your selves, but it is the gift of God.</hi> The mother indeed cals the childe to take the breast, while it cannot go (as we say) <hi>on high lone.</hi> But when all is done, the mother is fain to lead the childe by the hand, or take it up, and pull out the breast for it. It is the mighty power of God to make so proud a creature as man, to see he hath no power in himself. And it is the speciall vertue of Christ, to make a man whose thoughts are so oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to Christ, to desire to come to Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ist if he could.</p>
                  <p>To the 3d. thing concerning humiliation, for not doing as he ought, complaining that his heart is not tender enough; not broken enough; we return this Answer: That the text and doctrine do not say, him that is <hi>humbled</hi> so much, or <hi>broken</hi> so much, but him that <hi>cometh</hi> he will in no wise cast out. Yea him that is but <hi>coming.</hi> So that though he be not broken to peeces, yet in whole he is broken off from all things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tangled him from coming to Christ. And to this is the promise made in the text. Therefore lay not too much stresse upon sensible humiliations. Take heed of undue considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of sorrow for sin. As thou must not (as some have) make sorrow for sin, <hi>A SIN,</hi> through immoderate despon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and drooping doubts of mercy; so thou must not make it a SAVIOVR, by reliance on it, rather then on free grace through Christ. Water may carry a ship to the ocean, and so to the rich Ports and Ilands in it; but water is no part of the frait of the ship. Do not hoist so many sails of self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnings, so as to over-bear the ship of thy soul so as to sink it. Dost feel the untowardnes of thine own heart? it is softnes of heart to feel the hardnes of heart. And there is a seeming
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117321:29"/> hardnesse in desertion that is rather from desertion, then from willing corruption; in the midst whereof, the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and struglings of heart towards God, are the heart melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that proceed from the inward workings of God upon the heart. <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.17.19. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>O Lord why hast thou made us to erre from thy waies?</hi> yet it followeth in the same verse, <hi>Return for thy servants sake.</hi> And verse 19. a clear confession of faith, <hi>We are thine.</hi> If when <hi>we are afflicted, our God is afflicted,</hi> so in the 9. ver: of that same Chapter, then surely he will put an end to <hi>our</hi> afflictions as <hi>his</hi> afflictions, as soon as may be most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18, 19. <hi>I have surely heard</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim bemoaning hmself thus: Thou hast chastised me, and I was chastised, as a bullock unaccustomed to the yoak: Turn thou me, and I shall be turned, for thou art the Lord my God. Surely after that I was turned, I repented, and after that I was instructed, I smote upon my thigh; I was ashamed, yea even confounded, because I did bear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of my youth.</hi> Then the Lord ecchoes to him thus: <hi>Is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim my dear son? is he a pleasant childe? For since I spake against him, I do earnestly remember him still. Therefore my bowels are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for him, I will surely have mercy upon him.</hi> And of all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions God will soonest remove them that are most prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to a souls coming to Christ. Those afflictions that are sent to move us out of our drowsie sitting still, shall not lye an houre, if lesse will do the thing. See the theef on the Crosse, and the Converts, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. God soon gladed the mournfull crucifiers of Christ, when once they were pricked at the very heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IIII. 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. Let or hindrance that retards a spirituall young con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from a free and full laying hold of Christ, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>The improbability</hi> (as he thinks) <hi>of Christs doing any thing for him to make him come to him,</hi> removed.</head>
                  <p>SAith he, I have waited thus <hi>long</hi> in ordinances, yet finde I little wrought in my self. My heart seems to be worse then the <hi>publicans,</hi> then the <hi>souldiers, Luk.</hi> 3. Then the <hi>goalers, Act.</hi> 16. Worse then that in <hi>persecuting Paul. Act.</hi> 9. Worse then
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117321:30"/> the hearts of those that <hi>crucified Christ. Act.</hi> 2. For all these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lented, and came into Christ. Yea worse in some sort then the devils, for they <hi>believe and tremble. Jam.</hi> 2. But my heart is an hell of sin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ans.</hi> The text and doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine set not down the precise point of time when, or how soon a man must come, or else he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits Christs receiving him; but when ever a soul is coming though a good while in coming, Christ will receive him. Yea while he is coming, he hath received of Christ. It is Christ that drew thee, or thou couldst not set one step forwards. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. Yea God the Father draws thee. <hi>None c m come to me</hi> (saith Christ,) <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. <hi>except God the Father draws him.</hi> Thou poore soul, judgest thy self. But God alone is the judge of conscience, and according to rules in his word doth he judge. Therefore unlesse thou takest his word whereby to judge, thy thoughts of thy self are not judicious, but a sinfull phantasie. <hi>Martyr Bradford</hi> said his heart was hell when he was coming fully to injoy Christ as fast as he could, like <hi>Elijah,</hi> in cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iots of fire; and had an heaven of grace, and apprehensions of glory in his heart. More particularly we answer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Christ hath set certain houres, wherein he will power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully manifest his effectuall call of men; the 3d: 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. &amp;c. to the twelfth houre. It may be he hath allotted thee the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. or 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. houre. Happy is he that after long waiting is saved at last. It argues much grace, patiently to attend upon Christ in ordinances, all the while (be it more or lesse) till Christ will be pleased to give fuller incomes of grace. <hi>Psal.</hi> 43.5. <hi>Psal.</hi> 130.6. Turn to the places, and read them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thy trouble for not profiting under ordinances, is the kindly working of ordinances upon thee. Physick works well, when it makes us a little sick. Though ordinances call for attendance on ordinances, yet it is their proper effect to turn pride of performances into despair, to the end that we may know that our services, are not our Saviours; and therefore to relye on Christ, and not on them. When Christ hath brought us to finde the means to be no mediators, then usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Christ comes in through means. Christ is a Physitian
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117321:30"/> that comes not for his fee, but when we feel our <hi>need</hi> of him, even of <hi>him,</hi> then he comes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A soul may truly stay on God in ordinances, when he cannot triumphantly joy in God by ordinances. <hi>Isa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>He that is in darknesse, and sees no light, yet let him trust in the Lord, and relye upon the God of his salvation.</hi> Still therefore thou seest the text and point bear down all objections afore them. Therefore, O thou poore soul, lay down thy weapons of dispute, and come in to Christ. As it is said, <hi>Isa.</hi> 5. <hi>What could the Lord do more for his vineyard;</hi> so here, <hi>What could the Lord say more to his vineyard?</hi> Therfore take heed of wilfull disputings, especially of pride, complements, or sullennesse of spirit. <hi>Psal.</hi> 77. And <hi>Psal.</hi> 73. when thou hast said and done all in object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against coming in to Christ; thou must be glad of him, whom for present thou indeavourest to put off.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> A pressing invitation of all sinners, all men, all kinds of tempers of spirit to come in to the out-stretched arms of mercy of Christ Jesus, upon the ground of his PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISE.</head>
               <p>BY authority of the main and grand Position, this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as the <hi>Cryer</hi> in the court of Christs mercy, makes a lowd, and shrill <hi>Oyees</hi> to all manner of <hi>men,</hi> at all <hi>times,</hi> by all manner of <hi>means,</hi> to come away to Christ, lest they forfeit their recognizances, that is, the injunctions, offers, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of salvation. Hear it O ye sons of men. For Christ is the most excellent thing in heaven. He is <hi>God in our nature.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Immanuel, Matth.</hi> 1. (which is applied for your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire salvation against all opposition, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.) The <hi>Gospel</hi> is the most excellent thing on earth. Tis a <hi>ministry of the Spirit.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>which takes of Christ and shews it unto us,</hi> and makes him <hi>glorious in our</hi> apprehensions. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.14. And <hi>our text and posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is the pickt flower, the choise rarity, the non-such of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117321:31"/> Gospel. Therefore come away, come away. For, 1. here is a <hi>promise,</hi> therefore come upon, and by this promise. 2. Here is a <hi>protestation</hi> with this promise, that Christ will in no wise cast you out. Therfore plead <hi>with</hi> Christ, <hi>for</hi> Christ, upon this <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested promise.</hi> And 3. there is in this protested-promise a most positive proposition and assertion, that <hi>if you come, you shall be received in.</hi> Therefore adhere to it, and own it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECTION I.</hi> Of Naked coming to Christ.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. HEre being a promise (as we said but now) in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the text and position, let men come to Christ. And, 1. <hi>Nakedly</hi> to Christ, because the promise is <hi>free.</hi> 2. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely</hi> to Christ, because the promise is <hi>full.</hi> 1. Come nakedly to Christ. As one said notably out of experience, <hi>Ego nudus nundum sequor Christum.</hi> I nakedly follow naked Christ. A soul must take <hi>naked Christ;</hi> pure single Christ; Christ for himself, not for by-ends. The person is better then the portion; and so to take him, is better far then otherwise. And a soul <hi>naked,</hi> stript of his own righteousnesse, and self-considerations of worth; and clothed with his own shame; ashamed of his own vilenesse, must thus take Christ. These things must not discourage, but quicken us to come to Christ. Though, poor soul, thou art never so naked and vile in thine own eyes, come to Christ. More care is to be taken, that thou evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically <hi>see</hi> thy nakednesse, then to <hi>fear</hi> thy nakednesse. So Christ labours with thee; namely, that thou really <hi>see</hi> thy nakednesse, and <hi>thereupon to come</hi> to him. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Thou art wretched, and miserable, and BLINDE, and naked. I counsell thee to buy of me white rayment, that thou mayest be clothed,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore though thou art naked, a meer poore sinner; so in <hi>essence,</hi> so in <hi>appearance;</hi> yet come away naked, bring nothing with thee but thy miserable <hi>self.</hi> As <hi>Joseph</hi> in Aegypt inviting his father down to him, said, <hi>Regard not your stuffe.</hi> We are proan to bring our own <hi>stuffe</hi> with us; something of our own to commend us to Christ. But this must not be. It mars all.</p>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:117321:31"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: I.</hi> The hindrance of naked coming to Christ by reason of A SINFƲLL SEEING OF ONES SELF, removed.</head>
                     <p>TWo things usually hinder a soul from this naked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Christ. 1. A <hi>sinfull seeing of ones self.</hi> 2. A <hi>sinfull censure of ones self.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. A sinfull seeing of ones self. For this usefull duty of seeing our sins may be done very sinfully. As when a man doth pore so <hi>much,</hi> and so <hi>amisse</hi> upon his sins, and sinfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that he is <hi>afraid</hi> or <hi>loath</hi> to come to Christ. So fallen <hi>Adam.</hi> This is like the ecclipss of the Sun; A little spotted Moon, to attempt to shadow the oeean of light in the vast Sun: one mans finite sins, imagined to be able to cloud infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy in God; which is unpossible. Divines deliver this as a safe and sweet rule;<note place="margin">☜</note>
                        <hi>That sight and sorrow for sin that puts us off from coming to Christ, is a sinfull sight and sorrow for sin.</hi> This kinde of sorrow is in likenesse a kinde of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> For it <hi>seems</hi> to be <hi>for Christ</hi> (as the word in Greek may be taken) but is <hi>indeed</hi> against Christ, as the practise of it is. As the Heathens feigned, that the bright Sun was every night drowned in the Sea, whiles the world was dark; so by our legall Christ-declining floods of tears we drown our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of Gods glorious mercy. The <hi>devil transforms himself sometimes into an Angel of light; and sometimes appears as he is, an angel of darknesse,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) He sometimes <hi>walks in dry places,</hi> (Matth. 12.43.) as well as at other times in wet, when in the swine he went into the Sea. My meaning is, he endeavours to make a poore soul environed with his sins to see and weep over them too <hi>little</hi> or too <hi>much.</hi> So as he can make this soul neglect Christ in either extreame, to a perishing, he cares not. <hi>But thou, O soul, that wilt be wise to salvation,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note>
                        <hi>never judge that temper of heart to be grace, to be good, or a friend to thee, or to Christ, that retardeth thy coming to Christ.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> Arias Mont. <hi>renders it</hi> In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</note> I suppose thou wouldst be loath in the least to be like <hi>Cain.</hi> This hindrance of which we speak, is a spice of his disease, who <hi>said,</hi> My <hi>Evil</hi> (so the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117321:32"/>
                        <hi>Hebrew</hi> word) <hi>is greater then I can bear;</hi> and <hi>WENT out from the presence of the Lord.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">*</note> And <hi>Judas</hi> was not damned immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and precisely for his furthering of the crucifying Christ (for 3000. guilty of the same sin, upon faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance are saved: <hi>Act.</hi> 2.) but for despairing of the mercy of God. Therefore, O drooping souls, consider how ill you do, when you make a stand, looking on your rotten sins, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to run to a living Christ. God made known to you your sins, not to drive you <hi>from</hi> beleeving, but <hi>to</hi> beleeving. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, to 27. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22, 23, 24. Therefore take heed of this despondencie, as having a shew of indevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to frustrate God of his designe. Tis an odious compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to equall thy ragged regiment of sins with the host of Gods mercies; to compare thy little earthly globe, and sands of sins with the stars, and sphears, and heavens of Gods free grace. Take heed of seeming to out-vote God; who saith, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.7, 8. <hi>Let the wicked man return to the Lord, and he will have mercy on him, &amp;c. and abundantly pardon</hi> (Hebr. <hi>will multiply to pardon) For my thoughts are not your thoughts; neither are your wayes my wayes: but as the heavens are higher then the earth, so are my wayes, and thoughts higher then yours.</hi> If you leave the promise of comfort, and stand off from Christ, your sore may run long enough: <hi>Psal.</hi> 77.2. <hi>The Psalmist did in a sort seek God, yet because he refused comfort, his sore ran, and ceased not.</hi> When the promises and consolations of God seem small (as tis said in <hi>Job</hi>) our sins will seem great. But on the contrary, when we admire the immense magnitude of divine mercie, sin will melt to nothing before it. When we put away promises of support, the horror of sin will tyrannise. When the Sun is down out of sight, the Moon will seem great; and when she is farthest off in a just opposition to the Sun, then she is at the full, and then most efficacious in the increase of diseases. Tis easie to apply this. Let not that <hi>Sun, Malach.</hi> 4.2. be far from us; let not us be far from those his <hi>healing wings.</hi> Let us do as <hi>Abraham.</hi> God said, <hi>he should have seed.</hi> He was <hi>aged.</hi> Therefore here was a proper place for <hi>hope. Sarahs wombe was dead,</hi> as in relation to bearing of children, therefore <hi>Abraham
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117321:32"/> in hope beleeved against hope. Rom.</hi> 4.18, 19, 20. As long as the promise, and promiser is alive, do not as <hi>Martha, Joh.</hi> 11. go about to dispute the soul into doubtings. But as the woman in the Gospel, cry after Christ, and go a step; dispute with him, and step another. Stil follow.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Qu.</hi> Would you not have me look on my sins. Yea, but not so as to look off of thy Saviour. Let thy left eye be on sin, but the right on Christ. See sin, and see it indeed, but to <hi>its</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, not to the <hi>prejudice of thy coming</hi> to Christ. The more sin, the more need of Christ. To see sin to the disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of sin, is thus to fee it. 1. To see its <hi>impiety,</hi> and polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore the more to loath it. 2. Its <hi>coosenage,</hi> at first it flattered thee to act it; and now it terrifies thee. What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son hast thou to stand still, to hear that rail at thee, when peace may be had in Christ? No wise malefactor, but would rather run to the King for a pardon, if he may, then stand to hear witnesses, Jury and Judge against him. King Jesus calls thee to come for pardon; and none can hinder thee if thou wilt come. 3. Its <hi>insufficiency</hi> to help it self. One sin cannot acquit another. Sinfull despairing sorrow is but a sorry plaister to all our sins. It adds to a malefactor sin, that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth to read for his life, when the mercy of the book is offered him. 4. Its <hi>necessitousnesse</hi> of a Saviour; as consequentially as all diseases interpretatively call for the Physitian. Thy sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for sin therefore should be to sorrow thy self from staying with sin, unto a forwarding thee to Christ. Doth thy heart tremble at sin, with an humble eye to God? there will God dwell to be thy settlement. <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Chap.</hi> 66.2. Doth any as <hi>Ephraim</hi> bemoan themselves for sin, breathing desires to God, God will eccho graciously to such, you <hi>are my dear sons. Jer.</hi> 31.18, 19, 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: II.</hi> Another hindrance of naked coming to Christ, by reason of A SIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FƲLL CENSƲRING OF ONES SELF, removed.</head>
                     <p>THe 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. thing that hinders many a poor soul from a clear coming off to Christ, a naked coming to Christ is his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117321:33"/>
                        <hi>sinfull self-censuring.</hi> That is, he censures himself without any divine rule, and sometimes besides the truth of former expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. To sentence ones self as some do; that <hi>God hath repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated me▪</hi> or <hi>God utterly forsaken me,</hi> is to judge without any divine rule. And many charge themselves heavily, that <hi>they are great, if not the greatest sinners;</hi> and that though they have been great hearers, yet (they say) they have nothing wrought in them; which is untrue upon former experience. For I ask such a one; Who gave thee this light in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy self? who put upon thee those impressions to hear so much? And how comest thou by those desires of more to be wrought in thee, or else thou shouldest account all nothing? can these come from any but from God? And is it nothing to see ones own nothingnesse? Is it not much to <hi>be poore in spirit,</hi> to <hi>mourn,</hi> to be <hi>hungry for more? Matth.</hi> 5. Take heed O soul, by such rash charges against thy self thou mayst in a kinde break all the Commandments,<note place="margin">☞</note> and so adde sin to sin. As, 1. to <hi>make God no God,</hi> if thou thinkest him not to be mercifull. 2. To <hi>commit idolatry,</hi> in advancing thy sins above Gods will and power to pardon. 3. <hi>To take Gods name in vain,</hi> to professe the Gospel, and yet dispute against the promises. 4. <hi>To profane the Lords</hi> day in keeping a rest for coming to Christ in ordinances, and yet not to come to Christ. 5. To dispise the Ministers of Christ. While they preach, thou doest impeach. Whiles they dispute, thou endeavourest to confute those comforts they bring out of the word. 6. To <hi>murther</hi> thy soul. 7. To commit spirituall <hi>adultery,</hi> going a whoring after thine own imaginations. 8. To <hi>steal</hi> spiritually: as to rob God of his due honour of his mercy. And to rob thy self of that peace that he offers thee, and consequently to rob others of those sweet experiences thou mightest hold out to others, if thou didst come in to Christ. 9. To bear <hi>false witnesse</hi> against thy self. And, 10. to give way to <hi>concupiscence</hi> against Gods complacency, and willingnesse to save thee in Christ. <hi>Paul</hi> would not do so, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. His concupiscence bred in him a coveting after Christ. If thou seest six evils in sin, to wit, <hi>folly, guilt, filth, power, bastardy,</hi> and <hi>sorrow,</hi> behold there are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:117321:33"/> 6000. that is, innumerable mercies in God, and merits, and excellencies enough in Christ, to heal all: viz: <hi>wisdom</hi> to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from the <hi>folly</hi> of sin; <hi>justification</hi> from the <hi>guilt</hi> of sin, <hi>sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> from the <hi>filth</hi> of sin, <hi>Redemption</hi> from the <hi>power</hi> of sin; <hi>Adoption</hi> from the <hi>bastardy</hi> of sin, and all to make thee <hi>glory in the Lord,</hi> against the sorrow of sin: 1 Cor. 1.30, 31. Gal. 4.5, 6. Therefore hy to God in Christ. If he will keep thee there by his <hi>power through faith,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> as in a <hi>garrison</hi> (so the Greek) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. do not thou keep garrison against faith,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> by the <hi>strong holds of thy carnall reasonings, notions,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. If God pitch his tabernacle of ordinances neer thee; and kindle in it a <hi>sacred fire,</hi> to give thee spirituall light and heat; do not thou kindle a <hi>strange fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</hi> and delight in the sparks thereof, in pleasing thy self in thy wilfull sullennes, lest thou <hi>lye down in sorrow. Isa.</hi> 50.11. by comparing the former <hi>v:</hi> this sence of this 11. <hi>v:</hi> will appear to be to our purpose. But if thou wilt obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of God through the redemption in Christ, he will sell thee cheap, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1. &amp;c. Tis but (as <hi>Austin</hi> well) to <hi>sell thy self,</hi> thine own <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> and wholly be ruled by the Lord, and thou shalt have it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: II.</hi> Of coming entirely to Christ, and removing the impediments.</head>
                  <p>VVE must not onely come <hi>nakedly</hi> to Christ, (as we have heard) but we must come <hi>entirely.</hi> That which hinders, is a lending one ear to Satan; whereas we should not change one word with him by way of assent. It was <hi>Eves</hi> sin that she did. We should, as <hi>James</hi> adviseth, <hi>Resist the devil, and then he will flie.</hi> That is, resist him at <hi>first motion,</hi> and resist him <hi>fully.</hi> Honour him not with the least attention, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then to defie his temptations. If he object thou art not <hi>elected;</hi> Answer, where doth Gods word tell me so? But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1. first 6. verses. If he say the <hi>time is past.</hi> Answer, as long as thou art alive the eleventh houre is not past. And that God still cals <hi>to day: Psal.</hi> 95. And the <hi>Now</hi> is the acceptable time: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. And thou hast some
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117321:34"/> desires to answer to these. If he suggest, that God <hi>passeth sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence against such as thou art</hi> in his word. Answer, thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not such but thou mayest do as <hi>Jonah,</hi> chap. 2. v. 4. <hi>I am cast out of thy sight, yet will I look towards thine holy temple.</hi> And mayest claim thy right in that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31. <hi>If we judge our selves, we shall not be judged of the Lord.</hi> But if Satan make thee flie upon thy self, saying, <hi>Thou art so bad, that it is above thy thoughts</hi> how God can pardon thee: Then minde what the word of God tels thee, that it is Gods proper prerogative to pardon that which <hi>is above thy thoughts: Isa.</hi> 55. Therefore O thou poore soul, come away to Christ, leave all, and flie to him in the promises. <hi>God</hi> saith, Come. <hi>Christ</hi> saith, Come. The <hi>Spirit</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Rev. 22.17. Isa. 55.1. Matth. 11.28. 2 Cor. 5.20.</note> Come. The <hi>Word</hi> saith, Come. The <hi>Ministers</hi> say, Come. <hi>Saints prayers</hi> cry, Come. <hi>Saints practise</hi> shew thou must come. Come, and thou shalt be welcome <hi>now</hi> as in the text. And at last entertained with, <hi>Come ye blessed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> An incitation of all to plead with Christ, for Christ, upon the PROTESTATION in the promise of the text; that he will IN NO WISE cast out them that come to him.</head>
               <p>VVE have heard of the <hi>O yes</hi> making <hi>proclamation</hi> in the court of Christs Gospel for all, of all sorts to come in to him. There wants but <hi>vous a vec,</hi> the appearance of men to this, saying as young <hi>Samuel, Speak Lord, for thy servant heareth.</hi> To effect this, we carry on the other two of the three heads before propounded. The 1. was for all men to come in to Christ, upon the ground of the PROMISE in the <hi>generall</hi> of the text, (of which we heard in the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <seg rend="sup">th</seg>. Chap.) The 2. is to plead with Christ, to attain Christ, upon the PROTESTATION in the particular expression of the text, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I will by no means</hi> cast out. The 3d: follows in the next
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117321:34"/> chapter. The 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. is the businesse of this chapter. When the <hi>Law</hi> hath pleaded with thy conscience, convincing and breaking thy heart for sin; plead thou in the <hi>Gospel</hi> with Christ for healing. The Lord likes it. <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Come let us rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son together.</hi> He pleads with thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31. And in the text. And Christ pleads for thee to his Father. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. &amp;c. If thou askest me how thou shouldst plead? I answer, tell Christ that this his protested promise, as other in the Gospel, is <hi>generall, free, full,</hi> and <hi>earnest:</hi> say unto him; <q rend="margQuotes">O Christ thy promise is GENERALL, to all that <hi>come,</hi> to all that are <hi>weary</hi> of staying away. Others have been bold to come in upon the generality of the promise, and were accepted. <hi>Act,</hi> 10.44. Therefore I that finde no rest in staying away, coming to thee upon the same ground, let me be accepted. Thou hast not excluded me by name more then others. If thou wouldest have damned me, thou mightest have done it long since. Thou saiest, thou <hi>acceptest a willing minde.</hi> I cry as the man in the Gospel; <hi>Lord I desire to beleeve, help mine unbelief.</hi> And thy promise is FREE. Who but thine own self could make thee make this promise? <hi>whiles it was not in thine own power?</hi> when it was in thy thoughts, it was onely <hi>thine,</hi> to make it; now made and uttered, it is <hi>mine</hi> to take it. Art not thou God? Therefore thou canst as well cease to be God, as cease to be good. As the Sun and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains cannot cease to shine, and run. This makes thee <hi>free;</hi> thou needst no creature-perfection to make thee more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly willing. And therefore thou dost not <hi>except,</hi> but <hi>accept</hi> of <hi>ungodly, sinners,</hi> enemies. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. And therefore though I am one of the worser of these, it is not <hi>what</hi> I am (that thou lookest to) but <hi>where</hi> I am, namely, whether I stand off, or whether I <hi>come in</hi> to thee. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39.40. compared with this, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. Thy promise also is FULL. <hi>Full</hi> of thy <hi>presence.</hi> Thou speakest in it. Thou offerest thy self in it. Thou art the kernel of it. (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.) Thou art entayled upon a poore soul by the promise. And tis <hi>full</hi> in the <hi>expression; Thou wilt in no wise cast out him that comes.</hi> And well mayest thou say so; for thou hast sworn, both <hi>negatively</hi> that thou <hi>desirest
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117321:35"/> not the death of a sinner:</hi> (Ezek. 33.11.) and <hi>affirmatively,</hi> that <hi>in the seed Christ (Gen.</hi> 22.17, 18.) compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16.) <hi>all the nations of the earth shall be blessed.</hi> And applyed with double emphasis to all that shall beleeve. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18. Can God-Christ be false or perjured? Thou hast said, <hi>Heb</hi> 6. tis <hi>impossible for thee to lye.</hi> And elsewhere, that <hi>Heaven and earth shall passe away, rather then an iota of thy word.</hi> If a thousand come not to thee; thou wilt be true to any one poore soul that comes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. Thou joyest, ten to one, in the <hi>lost groat</hi> found; yea ninty nine to one in the <hi>lost sheep</hi> brought back again. Lastly, thy promise is EARNEST, saying, I will not, I will not, (as tis in the language of thy Spirit) <hi>cast out him that comes to me.</hi> As if thou didst direct y answer to my doubts of heart. If that say, Christ will <hi>cast me out;</hi> thou sayst, <hi>I will not.</hi> If that say again, I fear he will cast me out. Thou sayest again, I <hi>will not:</hi> as intimating, I need not fear. Sure dear Christ thou art <hi>in earnest,</hi> thou art so <hi>earnest,</hi> in that so long after this promise in the text, thou comest a woing to my unworthy soul: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Now we are embassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech you by us, we pray you in Christs stead be ye reconciled to God.</hi> Though man fall off; be dull to come, grow cold, and worse, as <hi>Laodicea, Revel.</hi> 3. yet <hi>there,</hi> at such a ones ear and heart thou <hi>standest knocking.</hi> Sweet Christ; though I have been a poore <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean,</hi> yet now I come.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Whiles thou thus pleadest in meditations, prayers, ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and disputations of soul, sure it cannot be (if thou persist) but the Spirit of Christ the mean-while pleads in thee for thee. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. For these words are the Scripture language of the Spirit. And these desires (if cordiall) cannot but be the breathings of the Spirit. And Christ will know the minde of his own Spirit. And when thou hast thus pleaded; observe what answeres Christ gives. Weigh that well. <hi>Psal.</hi> 85.8. For that is the issue of a plea. <hi>v.</hi> 1. And when Christ hath answered by letter or tokens, by words or deeds, look to 4. things.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:117321:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Look to Christs IMPRESSIONS upon thy spirit, <hi>namely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy heart be</hi> the epistle of Christ, written with the Spirit of the living God.</head>
                  <p>WHether thou <hi>receivest of Christs fulnesse grace for grace. Joh.</hi> 1.16. (though not with such brightnesse and clearnes of impression, yet with reality &amp; truth of ingraving) &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the heart motions of Christ, there be due ecchoings of thy spirit? as <hi>Psal.</hi> 27.8. (in manner of an eccho repeating the last word) <hi>Thou saidest, Seek my face: my heart said, Thy face Lord will I seek.</hi> And as <hi>Peter, Joh.</hi> 21. when Christ asked him, <hi>Peter loves thou me?</hi> He answers, <hi>Lord thou knowest I love thee.</hi> And thou hast in this discerning of thy self, warrant to take thy self at thy <hi>best,</hi> and in thy general good purposes of thine heart (for so Christ takes <hi>Peter</hi> there, and so thee) not at some worse particular ill fit. As <hi>David</hi> (a man of great weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses) so looks on himself, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Then shall I not be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med when I have RESPECT to</hi> (though I cannot EFFECT) all thy Commandments. And, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.23. <hi>He exhorted them with PVRPOSE of heart to CLEAVE to the Lord.</hi> Thus God-Christ looks on all his: he takes them at the best, mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their excellences, being silent of their weaknesses. So he mindes <hi>Abraham, Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Sarah,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>Elijah, Jam.</hi> 5. Christ is thy judge; thou must judge of thy self as he judgeth. If in a court of justice, onely the evil of the cause should be pleaded, what cause would prevail? so in the court of conscience. <hi>Psal.</hi> 130.3. <hi>If thou Lord shouldest mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand?</hi> But sure God doth not condemne all. And therefore it follows, <hi>But there is forgivenesse with thee, that thou mayst be feared.</hi> Thou <hi>sayest</hi> thou art dim, and dull, but what breaths the desire of thy soul? Haply that saith, <hi>O that I were any thing but sin.</hi> O that I suffered <hi>any change, so as my heart were changed.</hi> If so; then (as one said) turn the palm, not the back of thine hand to this staffe of comfort. That is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of flirting it off, grasp it to stay thy self. If a man shall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117321:36"/> give to a begger, and being importuned by him to give more, shall ask the begger, did I give thee nothing afore? and the begger shall say, nothing, because a small thing; were not this a just provocation to the Donor, to give no more? To acknowledge thankfully what Christ hath given, is the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall way to come by more.<note place="margin">*</note> As tis sin to have no grace; so tis sin to say we have no grace when we have.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: II.</hi> Look to the PACIFICATION of Conscience.</head>
                  <p>HAth Christ quieted thee in all the dark clouds of all thy failings, with that <hi>Aurum-potabile</hi> Antidote? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24, 28. <hi>Being justified FREELY by his grace through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Christ Jesus, we conclude a man is justified by faith without the deeds of the Law.</hi> Then bring thou, at all times of appearance of any guilt, thy sins under this generall pardon. Thus agree with <hi>all thy adversaries.</hi> And when thy conscience comes to yeeld to Gods free grace, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiesse in it as sufficient and benevolent to pardon all, then hast thou recorded thy evidence. And therefore when thou canst not see thy evidence, go to the records. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19▪ 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III. 3.</hi> Look to the SƲBJECTION of thy will.</head>
                  <p>HAth Christ brought down, and subjected to thy consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration all his good will towards thee? See what sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of will is in thee to close with him. Be it far from thee to have a gainsaying will. A <hi>Rachel</hi>-like disposition is most prejudiciall to thee. She <hi>would not</hi> be comforted. She <hi>might</hi> but <hi>would not.</hi> And far be it from thee to complement off thy comfort, as <hi>Peter did, Christs washing of his feet:</hi> Joh. 13. His obedience not checking his modesty, Christ sharply checkt him. But it may be thou <hi>doest not</hi> subject, because yet thou <hi>canst not,</hi> If this be the case, stand still, hearken diligently
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117321:36"/> what God saith; for he will effect it in thee whiles he is speaking: <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.45. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. weigh the places. If thou hearkenest to thy untoward will; it will be like a wrangling adversary, who, when thou hast had thy cause heard at <hi>Common</hi> Law (the law morall) and there <hi>Christ hath been the end of the law to thee for righteousnesse by faith. Rom.</hi> 10.4. And at <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> law of the Gospel of Christ (as tis said, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, by this <hi>Canon</hi>) that assures thee Christ is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thee; and at the <hi>Chancery</hi> and Court of <hi>Requests,</hi> God proceeding with thee according to <hi>equity,</hi> in relation to Christs satisfaction and Gospel orders, and hears thy <hi>requests,</hi> prayers, and supplications, and at all these Courts hast pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured thy p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace; yet still (as long as some corruption in it, and thats for all thy life) it will be still troubling thee, to put thy assurance to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rbitration, between flesh and blood, &amp;c. But when Christ thy King, and his Law is satisfied, what needest thou to regard any accuser whatsoever. Therefore conclude this thus; I will beleeve God, I will beleeve in Christ, though I perish. If I perish, I perish.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IIII. 4.</hi> Look to thy adhesion, thy adhering to Christ in practise.</head>
                  <p>THat is, wait, and attend on Christ in his ordinances; to maintain that evidence and assurance he holds out unto thee. Kings will maintain their Patents. Let not therefore men, or devils draw thee to confer with them against the word of Christ. If they will speak, and force thee to hear, answ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r as, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>If an angel of heaven bring any doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Gospel, let him be Anathema.</hi> The summe of which Gospel is, God is most mercifull through Christ to poore humbled sinners. Therefore if it be objected by thy adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>Thou hast no grace:</hi> Answer. Christ comes at first to the soul when it hath no grace. If it be objected thou must have faith. Answer: Christ brings it with him Tis his gift, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. And I have a <hi>will</hi> to beleeve, and that God <hi>accepts.</hi> If it be objected, that perhaps thou art not elected. Answer. God propounds
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117321:37"/> the doctrine of election for comfort as much to thee, as to any others. And that if thou art <hi>called,</hi> thou art <hi>elected: Rom.</hi> 8. If it be objected, those that are justified, are also sanctified: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. Answer; yet not so sanctified in this life, as to be free from all corruption: <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. If the <hi>will</hi> be sanctified, thats evidence that we are so much sanctified, as to be a seal we are justified: <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. And if we had no sin, we needed no Advocate; who is provided for us for all our lives, because we are not free from all corruption, all our lives. Thus thou seest how to plead with Christ, upon the promise, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of the promise. Do it; do it; he loves these holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences. <hi>Jacob</hi> will not let him go; therefore he will blesse <hi>Jacob</hi> ere he go. <hi>The kingdom of heaven</hi> (Matt. 11.12.) <hi>suffereth violence, and the violent take it by force.</hi> Christ loves this <hi>love-sicknesse of the soul.</hi> And therefore though the <hi>Spouse</hi> discontented him away by her sluggishnesse in her sleepinesse; yet she awakened, and being exceeding sick with love, he will be found again, and not chide her; her love prevailed with his love to cover all failings: <hi>Cant.</hi> chap. 5. and chap. 6. compared together.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> A perswasion of all men to own, and to adhere to Christ up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>positive</hi> ASSERTION of his promise, that those that come <hi>shall be received in,</hi> which is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuin sense of that hyperbolicall <hi>meiosis,</hi> he <hi>will in no wise cast out.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt every poore soul, well weighing this text, closely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to Christ. Although thou canst not at all times act faith of <hi>recumbence,</hi> to quietly and triumphantly acquiesce in an actuall injoyment of Christ, yet act faith of <hi>adherence,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Christ, as the Evening-star doth the Sun. Herein thy work is threefold, namely, 1. catch nothing but Christ. 2. leave all that is not Christ. 3. close dexterously and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically with Christ.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:117321:37"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT: I.</hi> Catch nothing but Christ.</head>
                  <p>CAtch nothing but Christ, catch at nothing but Christ; own nothing but Christ. Whatever a man may have without Christ, own it not instead of Christ. <hi>As</hi> all <hi>common</hi> graces, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>viz:</hi> elumination, conviction, restriction, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. And all the <hi>graces of the foolish virgins, Matth.</hi> 5. which we distinctly numbred afore in Chap. 10. Sect. 3. And <hi>all that was in the stony and thorny ground.</hi> All which we know by woful experience out of the Scriptures, were had, yet Christ left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde.<note place="margin">☜</note> Some men when they hear in the word that God is willing to pardon sinners, they say in their hearts, and not without some stony <hi>ground affection,</hi>
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">THATS WELL, GOOD NEWS, LET HIM DO IT. And so wholy leave it to God to look to if he will save them; but they never challenge Christ to that end.</hi> But as we are injoyned in the word to hear Christ, and apply Christ there offering himself; so we must take heed of doting, and resting on, or in any thing but Christ; of imbracing a bright cloud instead of the Sun of righteousnesse. <hi>Malach.</hi> 4.2. of imbracing a shadow, instead of the substance: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1. and 11.1. Which latter place, that <hi>faith</hi> is the <hi>substance</hi> of things hoped, is true both of <hi>fides quae creditur,</hi> the <hi>doctrine</hi> of faith <hi>which</hi> is believed, it contein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christ, and of <hi>fides quâ creditur,</hi> the <hi>quality</hi> of faith <hi>with which</hi> we believe, it laying hold of Christ the substance. See how Christ doth besiege thee, as well as beseech thee to yeeld and come in to him. In 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. we shewed afore he doth <hi>beseech thee.</hi> In <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. he shews thy straits in which thou art without him: namely, poore and miserable, and blinde, and naked. Read the book of experience, how miserable men of the greatest injoyments have been without Christ. As <hi>Dives</hi> with all his <hi>riches; Herod</hi> with all his <hi>honour; Judas</hi> with all his parts; <hi>Hypocrites</hi> with all their laboursome performances, and seeming profession. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. All things, parts, privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, &amp;c. without Christ, not bringing thee to own, and be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:117321:38"/> owned of Christ, will <hi>cast thee out. Matth.</hi> 7.22.23. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.10, 11. And verse 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46. But Christ imbraced by faith, will not cast thee out. So our Text and Position. Christ amidst al things below, as outward mercies, or spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all means of grace, is like the <hi>Ark</hi> in the midst of the waters, of <hi>Noahs flood,</hi> or Jordan. They that were in, or with the Ark escape drowning. No others. The word, <hi>Baptisme,</hi> Lords <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> in fine prove nothing, unlesse they really exhibite, and thou really receive from them Christ. Ordinances the <hi>field,</hi> but Christ the <hi>treasure</hi> in that field.<note place="margin">*</note>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. And behold a dolefull experiment in these evill times: those that many yeers have dallyed with ordinances, not therein receiving Christ, now fall off of ordinances, and slight Christ: a just judgement of God.<note place="margin">Qu.</note> If thou dost demand; when do I <hi>in</hi> all, and <hi>above</hi> all, either ordinances, promises, &amp;c. look on, and take up Christ?<note place="margin">An.</note> We answer: when ye look on all but as the tools, the taking of Christ the great work, and the end of that work; and yet challenge him as your own. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. So that there flows thence some drawing power; some grounded peace; and some effectuall and effective love. After severall wooings, the heart it more drawn out, contentment increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, and love abounds to a conformity in manners.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Leave all that is not Christ, for Christ.</head>
                  <p>LAy by all that is not Christ, to come to Christ himself; and the things entailed on Christ. Set to the work of stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying him as the Spouse in the Canticles throughout, that thy soul may be wholly taken up with admiration of him, as the Spouse was. Give thy self to the businesse of divine and spirituall consideration of Christ in the promise, 1. as the onely <hi>good:</hi> 2. As the onely <hi>truth.</hi> 3. As the onely <hi>efficacie</hi> of the promise.</p>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:117321:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: I.</hi> To consider Christ as the onely GOOD of every promise.</head>
                     <p>DOth any promise offer thee frendship, honour, riches, pleasures? All these, of the world are some contentment with Christ to relish and sauce them. But these kinde of things are far more eminent in Christ. Therefore let the goodnesse of Christ bribe thine heart to give it self to him. The cause is more excellent then the effect. And the body of the Sun is more glorious then the beams. Therefore say to these, <hi rend="margQuotes"> either help me forward to Christ, let mammon, &amp;c. be my <hi>freinds</hi> towards Christ, or else stand by, and give roome for Christ who is farre more worth then you all. <hi>Wisdom,</hi> saith Solomon, <hi>is good with an inheritance:</hi> or if they will not conjoyn; </hi> wisdom is more excellent without an inheritance; then an inheritance without wisedom. <hi>Christ is the wisdom of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. And be sure the man that hath Christ hath all things. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. three last. Or if he hath but Christ, he hath of <hi>him</hi> better then all things; and in him <hi>God</hi> (as tis there) who as better, so <hi>more</hi> then <hi>all</hi> things. We cannot say <hi>all</hi> (properly) of an <hi>infinite;</hi> but in <hi>that,</hi> we have more then all. Therefore seeing so much is in Christ, and comes with Christ, let the goodnesse of Christ out-bid all offerers; out-shoot the devil, and the world in their own bowe. Do they tempt thee with that they call good? Tell them, neerer the fountain waters are sweeter. And the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity is more fresh, and unbraded in the Artificers hand. And further tell them, that all promises are couched in that promise of Christ. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. Christ is so good he makes the promise cheap to him that leaves all for him. The Disciples had left all for Christ, yet they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of it, nor tell where to be so well. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.68. Christ is so good, that thou needest not seek about, to bring any good of thine own: <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Buy without money,</hi> that is, without self-worth, or sufficiency. Thy work in the text is to see that there is no help for it, but thou must <hi>come;</hi> and coming must <hi>rowle</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:117321:39"/> thy self on <hi>him.</hi> We seeing our selves poore; we mourn for it. We think a good match would help all. We marry a wealthy person, and so are made rich. In the same moment of <hi>time</hi> we are married, and made rich; but in order of nature we are first married, then endowed by the party we are married to. All this is true civilly; but more, and more certainly true spiritually, and is the main of my meaning. If a man in need shall presume he may borrow all requisites, and not buy, when they may be bought cheaply, but cannot be borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he may starve. Still my meaning is spirituall. Compare the foolish virgins, <hi>Matth</hi> 25. and <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1. together. And tis much at one to buy that which will not serve our turn. So in that, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.2. In pain to cry, and walk up and down, and not come to the physitian, is to little purpose. Tears, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in performances, without coming to Christ, in, and by them, is to do as good as nothing. To look for any thing in duties, without God in Christ, is a kinde of borrowing, and taking, and using that which will be taken from us. But to take Christ himself in duties, by faith that worketh by love, this is according to Gods phrase, <hi>a buying</hi> of what will do us good indeed; be our own, and never be taken from us. Make not the commodity of salvation <hi>cheaper</hi> then God makes it;<note place="margin">☞</note> as to cast off ordinances, family duties, secret devotions. These thy posture, thy duty, thy gesture in waiting on Christ. And make it not <hi>dearer</hi> then God makes it; as to say, if thou couldst first master thy sins, live a little better, then I would go to Christ. Thou must first come to <hi>Jordan,</hi> to <hi>Bethesda,</hi> &amp;c. and then be healed there. The best repentance comes after faith in Christ. Therefore, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. there is expresse the double repentance of those Converts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: II.</hi> Consider Christ as the onely TRƲTH of every promise.</head>
                     <p>COnsider Christ so the main of every promise, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> makes the promise <hi>true</hi> in <hi>veritie,</hi> and makes the <hi>truth</hi> of the promise in the <hi>substance.</hi> Christ is THE TRUTH: <hi>Joh.</hi>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:117321:39"/> 14.6. And he is THE TRUTH IN THE PROMISE: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. And he hath ingaged God upon giving him to a man, that man a shall have all promises made good to him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. So that if we take up Christ in the promise, we have all promises fulfilled, at least <hi>originally,</hi> and <hi>vertually,</hi> till anon formally as far as is for our <hi>good.</hi> In the same, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8. For all the promises are made to the head; and all entayled on us, upon condition of having him: <hi>ibid. Rom.</hi> 8.32. As nothing is <hi>except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> from him, so he shall not be <hi>separated</hi> from us, as God is not from him: <hi>ibid. Rom.</hi> 8. Now God <hi>doth</hi> not, <hi>will</hi> not, nay <hi>cannot</hi> lye: <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. therefore his promises cannot, though long ere all performed. <hi>Habac.</hi> 2.3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> But I have waited exceeding long for comfort, and more grace, and yet have it not.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ans:</hi> Till it come, live by faith on the promise. Then will he come that is in the promise, with his power and efficacy. The summe of all is this; make the promise thy securitie, thy safetie, thy sanctuary. Therein thou hast Christ bound, and hast him in hold till he perform.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PARAG: III.</hi> Consider Christ the EFFICACY of all the promises.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou hearest the promise speak; say, The <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, lightning, earthquake, and fire of the Law terrifying me is over; this the still voice God is here.</hi> Now Christ more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately speaks to me. The promise is the <hi>breathing</hi> of Christ: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. compare <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. the <hi>chariot</hi> of the Spirit: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. The <hi>image</hi> of Christs minde,<note place="margin">☜</note> as a word is the image of a mans minde. Say, I must not bring faith with me to the promise, but fetch faith from the promise. We cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve before we have the promise. <hi>Psal.</hi> 85.8. He will SPEAK: and not onely <hi>peaceable</hi> things, but the PEACE it self. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation is as a 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. Creation: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. So that the Gospel is a 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. <hi>Genesis.</hi> We may as well imagine to see the Sun without its own beams, or reap seed without sowing seed; as to have faith before we come to consider the promise. Wait therefore
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:117321:40"/> on the promise, for Christ is in the promise, the efficacy of the promise. Christ inlightned and enlivened the disciples by opening to them the promises: <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. And with the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses holding forth Christ came in the Spirit: <hi>Act.</hi> 10.45. And with the promise came their joy. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Close with Christ in the promise.</head>
                  <p>HEre is the main thing, this comes to the quick of the businesse to close with Christ in the promise. That thou mayst there receive thus to do, bespeak thy Christ in these, or the like soliloquies. <q rend="margQuotes">O Christ, all thy <hi>doings</hi> shew thee a <hi>Mediator.</hi> All thy word shew thee willing to be an <hi>husband</hi> to my soul, in it thou comest a woing (<hi>Prov.</hi> 1.2, 3, &amp;c. to 10. Chap. and <hi>Canticles</hi> throughout: and in all the new Testament) Thou hast <hi>dipt thy garments in blood</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain me. <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.1. &amp;c. Thou wouldest own me in order of nature and working before I owned thee. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6. Thou givest thy self to me; then me to thee: <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. and 16. <hi>v.</hi> and 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.19. Therefore my soul desireth to own thee as a <hi>Mediator,</hi> to advance thee in my heart as an <hi>Husband;</hi> to eccho to thy Gospel. Thou woest my <hi>consent,</hi> I desire to give thee my <hi>good will.</hi> And thou hast said thou acceptest of the <hi>will.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. Yea, O Christ, thou and I in part are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; thou hast my <hi>flesh, and so neerer to me then Angels. Heb.</hi> 2. So that in a sence, <hi>We twain are one flesh.</hi> And thou hast said, we <hi>shall be one spirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. And thou hast prayed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. <hi>that I might beleeve,</hi> and <hi>that thou and I might be one,</hi> as thou and the Father are one: <hi>ibi:</hi> oft. And I know thee to be most excellent, and I desire to have thee, because thou art most excellent. I know thee in part, therefore I would have thee; and I would have thee, that I might more and better know thee; and seeing there is nothing good in me by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I know not whence these should be, unlesse from thy Spirit. Therefore I am emboldned to own thee as mine, or at least to be mine. Whatever thou dost, or what ever I do, I will own thee, close with thee, hold close with thee. And
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:117321:40"/> the more thou dost quicken, and comfort me with more hope since I made these addresses, these approches to thee, (for since I came neer thee, my soul hath been refresht) the more I will adhere to thee, &amp; make my reliance upon thee. I own thee, and by thy grace will own thee in all thou <hi>art,</hi> in all thou <hi>saiest,</hi> in all thou <hi>dost.</hi> I will own thee as mine, in all my <hi>hearing,</hi> in all my <hi>praying,</hi> I will own thee in all my <hi>doings,</hi> and performances; I will through thy help live and die with this in my heart and mouth, <hi>Thou Christ art mine, and I am thine; thine, and thine only.</hi> And if while I live, thou O Christ, wilt whip me with afflictions; yet now hence forward, since I have seen, and felt, and tasted in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure what thou art, my hope is I shall not be whipt from thee. My resolution is <hi>Job's, Though thou kill me, yet I will trust in thee.</hi> If thou whip me, yet I will weep after thee. If thou strike me, yet with all instruct me, and to come still to thee, I shall beleeve what thou hast spoken. <hi>Psal.</hi> 94.12. that <hi>therein I am blessed, and not cursed.</hi> If, O Christ, thou shalt at any time dispute against me, as against the woman in the Gospel; I shall desire the boldnesse humbly to contest with thee as she did. If thou tellest me I am a <hi>dog;</hi> I will confesse I am, till I meet with thee. But thou canst tranform a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent into a rod.</hi> And more, thou saiest we are <hi>symmorphosed, (Rom.</hi> 8.) yea <hi>metamorphosed</hi> into thine image. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. last. If thou saiest, <hi>Bread is for the children;</hi> my reply is, give me the bread, THEE the bread, (as thou hast said, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.) and I shall be made a childe. If thou frown upon me, that I cannot see one beam, onely I perceive thou art in the roome in the dark, I will even follow thine own counsell. <hi>Isa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>He that feareth the Lord, and obeyeth the voice of his servant; that walketh in darknesse, and sees no light, let him trust in the name of the Lord, and stay upn his God.</hi> If thou thunder over me with the Law; yet by grace I shall not despair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I see Gospel in the Law. Thou art there said to be <hi>my God, that brought me out of bondage in Egypt,</hi> thou, O Christ, art he that was <hi>brought out of Egypt (Matt.</hi> 2.15. According to the prophesie, <hi>Hos.</hi> 11.1.) and I in thee. Tis there said thou <hi>hast mercy for thousands of generations,</hi> of which I beleeve my
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:117321:41"/> self to be one, thy word not excluding me more then others: Thy law is but an appendix to the Gospel, and answers to the law of sacrifices, holding forth thee slain for our sins, as in the new Testament, love answers to faith. The sacrifices teach me faith in thy blood, and the morall law teacheth me love in obedience. If thou wilt not at this time say to my heart thou wilt love me; yet I resolve to love thee. If thou wilt not at any time look on me, I will look on thee. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I cannot cleerly look on thee, I will patiently look for thee. The Sun that sets, will rise. Thou art that Sun, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. If thou wilt not receive me yet <hi>as a Spouse,</hi> I am contented to be thy <hi>servant.</hi> If thou wilt not do something that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth me, I will endeavour to please thee; namely, I will wait upon thee. For I know thy good wil is better then al works. If thou wilt not do for me that which seems good to me, do that seems good to thee. For thou canst not but do like thy self. Thou <hi>art good, and therefore thou wilt do good. Psal.</hi> 119. If I cannot joy in all thy actings towards me; I have cause to joy in thee thy self. I may well bear some sharp passages from so excellent a one as thou art. If, O Christ, thou dost at any time make my sins testifie against me (as against <hi>Job</hi>) I will acknowledge my sins; but bring thy word to testifie against thee that thou shalt not condemne me, nor will I despair of thy mercy; but rest upon this text, and all the other glorious promises formerly quoted to open it. And lastly, if, O Christ, thou dost at any time leave me in a deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I have not such feeling apprehensions of thee; yet I will not, I cannot desert thee. If I leave thee, I loose me, looose all. I will learn of <hi>David,</hi> yea of thy self, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.1. <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. how to behave my self in desertion. If I cry once, <hi>Thou hast forsaken,</hi> I will say twice, <hi>My God, my God.</hi> And I will demand the reason <hi>why? why hast thou forsaken.</hi> For I know there is no reason thou shouldst utterly forsake me, because thou sawest reason in thine own heart of love to promise the contrary, with the greatest vehemency of expression. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5. <hi>By no means will I ever leave thee; no, no by no means will I ever forsake thee:</hi> so that I have no more to think, or say, but <hi>AMEN.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>